Atty. Renato N. Bantug Jr.: Officer of the Impeachment Court and the Senator Judges.
Sen. Sherwin T. Gatchalian: The
Sen. Sherwin T. Gatchalian: Sergeant at Arms is directed to make the proclamation.
Alfredo Sotto Corpuz: All persons are commanded to keep silent under pain of penalty while the Impeachment Court is in session for the trial of Vice President Sara Zimmerman Duterte.
Sen. Sherwin T. Gatchalian: The Impeachment Trial of Vice President Sara Zimmerman Duterte is hereby called to order. We shall be led in prayer by Senator Alan Cayetano.
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: Holy Father, we come to you today, different ages, galing po sa Luzon, Visayas, Mindanao, iba-iba po ang paniniwala sa politika, sa religion, pero lahat po ay Pilipino at lahat po ay ginagalang ang pangalan mo. Sinabi niyo po sa Propetang Jeremiah, sa Jeremiah 29.11, For I know the plans I have for you, plans to prosper you and not to harm you. Plans to give you hope and a future. You love us so much that you made us in your nature and likeness, giving us free will. Thus, to receive the fruits of your plans, plans to prosper us and not to harm us, plans to give us hope and a future, we must first seek your kingdom and righteousness. You call us to be faithful, Lord God, for us to be faithful both in small things and in big things. Same with the rules, Mr. President. Help us to be faithful with the Constitution, the Senate rules, the rules of impeachment. Help us to be faithful to the rules of fairness. As the prosecution stated yesterday, to hold everyone accountable, from the barangay captain to the highest official of the land. Lord God, Holy Spirit, do not allow us to obstruct justice. Yet, always give us the strength to obstruct injustice. Regardless of the cost and the consequences, magalit na po kung sino magagalit, gamitin niyo kami bilang instrumento ng hustisya. Lead each one of us to pursue the impeachment trial with fairness, political neutrality, and due process. To pursue the flood control scandal with the same zeal, effort, fairness, and political neutrality. To pursue corruption in all forms. Help us build a justice system that is ideal rather than one that is weaponized and is actually an instrument of oppression and tyranny. We may disagree on many things, but let us agree in asking for your love, grace, and mercy upon the nation. We may have different visions of a prosperous Philippines, of accountability and fairness, yet may we agree in the words you put in the framers of the Philippine Constitution, which is found in the Preamble. We, the sovereign Filipino people, imploring the aid of Almighty God in order to build a just and humane society and establish a government that shall embody our ideals and aspirations, promote the common good, conserve and develop our patrimony, and secure to ourselves and to our posterity the blessings of independence and democracy under the rule of law. And a regime of truth, justice, freedom, love, equality, peace do ordain and promulgate this Constitution. Thank you for this privilege to serve you and our people, Lord God. We ask for all of this in Jesus' mighty name.
Sen. Sherwin T. Gatchalian: Amen.
Atty. Renato N. Bantug Jr.: Atty. Judge De La Rosa, Atty. Judge Ejercito, Atty. Judge Estrada, Atty. Judge Goh, Atty. Judge Ontiveros, Atty. Judge Lacson, Atty. Judge Lapid, Atty. Judge Legarda, Atty. Judge Marcoleta, Atty. Judge Marcos, Atty. Judge Padilla, Atty. Judge Pangilinan, Atty. Judge Soto III, Atty. Judge Tulfo Erwin Atty. Setor Judge Tulfo Rafi, Atty. Setor Judge Villanueva, Atty. Setor Judge Villar Camille, Atty. Setor Judge Villar Marc, Atty. Setor Judge Zubiri, Atty. The Presiding Officer, Atty. Setor Judge Escudero, Atty. The Senate President.
Sen. Sherwin T. Gatchalian: With 20 senators present, the
Sen. Sherwin T. Gatchalian: Chair declares the presence of a quorum. We now recognize the Presiding Officer, Senator Chiz Escudero.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Thank
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: you, Mr. Senate President.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: The reading of the Journal of July 6, 2026 of the Senate sitting as an Impeachment Court is hereby dispensed with and unless there are any objections, the same is hereby approved and adopted. The Clerk of Court will now please read and call the case before this Impeachment Court.
Atty. Renato N. Bantug Jr.: Case number 004-2026 in the matter of Impeachment Trial of Vice President Sarah Zimmermann Duterte.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Appearances.
Rep. Gerville “Jinky Bitrics” R. Luistro: Good afternoon, your honors. Same appearance for the prosecution. We are ready, your honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Noted. Appearances for the respondent.
Sheila C. Sison: Good morning, Your Honor. Same appearances for the defense.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Is the prosecution ready to call its first witness?
Rep. Gerville “Jinky Bitrics” R. Luistro: Yes, your honor. However, the prosecution have few concerns which it wanted to raise before the honorable impeachment court. So, may I request, your honor, that the honorable... Counsel for the Prosecutor, Lorna P. Kapunan, be recognized, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Before recognizing the Council for the Prosecutor, Ma'am, upo muna kayo. Chair would like to recognize first, Senator Judge Lacson. What is the pleasure of the Honorable Lacson? You
Sen. Panfilo “Ping” M. Lacson: may proceed, Sir. Yes, Mr. Senate President, Mr. Presiding Officer, Your Honors. Just so it will be clear to our fellow... As well as the panel of prosecutors, the defense team, and the public in general, yesterday after your election as presiding officer, you delivered your opening statement, portions of which I will either quote or paraphrase as follows. You stated, the Constitution states that conviction can only happen with the concurrence of two-thirds of all members of the Senate. And then you continued. With 24 members of the Senate, a literal interpretation of this means that conviction requires the affirmative vote of at least 16 senator judges. However, you also made it clear that, and I quote, those who disagree have the right to go about it through a legal challenge and sue the Supreme Court by virtue of its power of judicial review. Render a different ruling on this question. The impeachment court shall faithfully abide by that ruling. My point of inquiry, Mr. President, Mr. Presiding Officer is, is this portion of your opening statement a matter of legal opinion on your part as Presiding Officer or does it constitute a ruling by the impeachment court? If the response is, it is the latter. Does this mean that this Court, through the Presiding Officer, has raised the level of discourse to a justiciable issue or a dispute that the Supreme Court may have legal authority to settle and resolve? In case either one or both panels in front of us decide to exercise their right to challenge the said ruling, should they deem it as a grave abuse of discretion by this Court? I submit.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: The response of the Presiding Officer is in the affirmative. In fact, the journal that we just approved contains a similar inquiry by Senator Judge Cayetano yesterday when he inquired if it was the position and ruling of the Presiding Officer and the Presiding Officer answered in the affirmative. So to clarify, yes, I believe it is It may be considered already as a justiciable controversy, although it is not for us to dictate that but the courts, given that it is a ruling of the chair not objected to nor appealed by any member of this court and therefore stands. Thank you for the clarification, Mr. Presiding Officer. Thank you, Senator Judge Lacson. Senator Judge Cayetano, what is your pleasure, sir?
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: Sir President, Presiding Officer, may I just further clarify this statement? You may proceed, sir. I confirm that yesterday we heard the same thing and when the transcripts come out of course then it will be available to everyone.
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: Basically yesterday I clarified whether that was the opinion of the elected presiding officer and of course without any offense to my brother and friend Senator Escudero, we have a continuing objection.
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: I asked him whether this was already a ruling of the court because if it's the ruling of the court, then as a threshold issue, we will have no further questions. Section 22, Article 22 of our rule says that all orders, decisions may be acted upon without objection or if objection is heard, the orders and decisions shall be voted on without debate by ayes and nays, which shall be entered in the record. Subject, however, to operation of Rule 6. And Rule 6 speaks of whether the presiding officer will rule on relevance, admissibility, and giving any move on two minutes. So I may also correct that yesterday I was not allowed to, when I objected to Senator Lacson, I should have been given ten minutes in accordance with Section 22. But I do admit that Before that, in the point of order, Senate President Gatchalian was liberal in allowing us to explain. Anyway, everything has been explained yesterday as part of the constitutional issue of the presiding officer. And since you allowed us to submit in writing, we will do so.
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: But
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: just on this point of the...
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: As of today, the stand of the impeachment court is that “all members” means that as long as you're still a member. So, meaning, when are you not a member anymore? When you die, when you are removed by finality, and when you resign. Otherwise, you are still a member, so you are still counted. And it is in that spirit that we ask—and we're preparing maybe a memoranda for all members—
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: to allow Senator Marcoleta and Senator Jinggoy, since they are going to have a vote. And if they are not allowed to vote, then that will be counted as a vote for acquittal, and that might be favorable to the defense rather than a part of giving a fair trial. So all I wanted to clarify today, Mr. President, is that we will continue to thresh out if there are any constitutional issues. But as of today, it is very clear that, as a court,
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: we have decided that two-thirds of 24—there are 24 members of the Senate today, 20 are present here today, but there are still 24 members—and 16 ang number of senators needed to convict on any of the articles, Mr. President, Mr. Presiding Officer. Thank you.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: What is the pleasure of Senator-Judge Pangilinan?
Sen. Francis “Kiko” Pangilinan: Thank you, Mr. Presiding Officer, Mr. Senate President. Just to place on record that I would like to clarify that the ruling of the Chair of 16 is as to the issue of whether the number—the threshold number—of conviction. The matter of whether or not Senators Marcoleta and Senator Estrada should be participating in the process of the trial is another matter that we will have to discuss perhaps in camera or on the floor at a later date, Mr. President.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Noted.
Rep. Gerville “Jinky Bitrics” R. Luistro: Your Honor, we respectfully reiterate our request that counsel for the panel of prosecutors, Atty. Lorna Capunan, be recognized.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Counsel for the panel of prosecutors, Atty. Lorna Kapunan is recognized. Will you be the one to present your first witness, ma'am?
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Good afternoon, Your Honors, Senate President, Presiding Justice. I do have a manifestation. Well, in direct answer to the query of the presiding senator-judge, I am not presenting the witness today. But I would like, with your permission, your honors, to manifest a query that we request be addressed by this honorable court presiding judge to the defense.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: The lady may proceed.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: We are informed and, in fact, we have seen an interview Conducted in the Senate premises on the Vice President herself. And she had been quoted as saying that she is expecting a bloodbath and a bludgeoning but she will not. Her head may be blooded but unbowed. My respectful query, Your Honors please, which could be directed to The defense counsels is if the vice president is in the premises, does she intend to appear personally before this impeachment court? And that is preliminary to another manifestation that I would like to make.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Or we'll simply answer the query of the counsel for the prosecution.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: This is relevant to the presentation that we will be making this afternoon, Your Honors. This court will recall your own statements, Mr. Presiding Judge, that on Tuesdays, every Tuesday of every week, that the prosecution must indicate who the witnesses they intend to present before this court will be. This is to enable the impeachment court To issue, when appropriate and if deemed necessary, a subpoena for such witness. And that is my query this afternoon because an end presentation of witness on the first article that we will be presenting which is grave threats and acts of sedition, Your Honor.
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: One of the key witnesses, hostile, albeit hostile, would be the vice president. And therefore, if we can inquire if it is her intention to again appear in the premises of the Senate because we are already respectfully informing this honorable court that we will manifest, that we will have a written request. for her presence in connection with this article on grave threats, Your Honor. That is the relevancy of my manifestation.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: The Chair would like to rule on the manifestation and request of the Council for Prosecutors instead of throwing the question To the Council for Respondents for the simple reason that I do not want the parties to engage in a debate before this court. You can very well do that with the presentation of your witness through direct and cross-examination, redirect and recross. To answer, the impeachment rules do not mandate nor require the respondent to attend any hearing or trial of the impeachment court. Whether she was in the building earlier or arrived after, It is totally up to the respondent because from the point of view of the court, she is represented in this court through her counsel already. Should the counsel for the prosecutors desire to call the respondent herself, the court will act on that motion and request once it is made and or filed and need not make a ruling at this point in time. Because of course, when that motion is made, we will ask the counsel for respondent
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: Thank
Atty. Lorna Patajo-Kapunan: you, thank you, sir presiding judge, justice, senator, judge. We yield to the wisdom of your decision. With that, we will reserve the right. We are not waiving the right to do call her at the appropriate time and to do file the appropriate request for subpoena duces tecum and subpoena ad testificandum
Rep. Gerville “Jinky Bitrics” R. Luistro: Atty. Tessie C. Candom To the head prosecutor of Article 4 that is threat, the Hon. Lawrence Defensor, may I request that he be recognized, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: The member of the panel of prosecutors, Congressman, the Hon. Lorenz Defensor is recognized for his introduction of Article 4, I presume.
Rep. Lorenz R. Defensor: Thank you so much, Mr. Presiding Officer. May I be allowed to make a manifestation? Before you
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: proceed, Senator Judge Cayetano is recognized.
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: That we also need time to study. So if we look at our rules of impeachment, suppletory kasi yung rules ng rules of court. And the difference between asking the accused to take the stand and asking someone who is not the accused, but we may say something that is incriminatory. There's a wide difference. So the accused, under the rules of court, hindi mo pwedeng i-force to take the stand. Pero yung hindi accused, they have to take the stand and wait for the question and then they can claim the right against self-incrimination. But it could be argued that this isn't exactly a criminal court and a criminal offense. It's an impeachment court. So if it pleases the court or if The prosecution is sure to ask for the subpoena. May I propose, Sir Presiding Officer, that both sides give us a memoranda in advance so that we can also do our part and study rather than...
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: Thank you for the interruption, Congressman.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: And we will be scheduling it for oral arguments by the parties. If that is the desire of the Honorable Senator Judge Cayetano, we will do the same with respect to this once the motion has been filed formally by the panel of prosecutors. The Honorable Defensor is recognized. You may proceed, Sir.
Rep. Lorenz R. Defensor: Thank you so much, Your Honor. Honorable Senator Judges, Noong kadalawang putdalawa ng Hunyo 2026, naggulat At nagdalamhati ang buong bansa sa pamamaril sa isang paaralan.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Atty.
Rep. Lorenz R. Defensor: Noong ikadalawampung dalawa... No, no, no. On all but one,
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: sir. Kindly finish your reply to the objection of counsel for respondent.
Rep. Lorenz R. Defensor: Allow us to freely advocate our positions through the proper and respectful discourse. This is not prohibited under the rules. In fact, the court has declared that yesterday the rules will not comply with the strict procedures of a judicial proceeding. Each article is a separate complaint and it would be the proper guidance for the senator judges, lalo na po sa ating mga kapwa-Pilipino na nanonood para mas lalo nilang maunawaan ang ipipresenta naming ebidensya. The impeachment is a sui generis. Sui generis dahil kakaiba ito, hindi ito judicial, administrative, or civil or criminal proceeding. Hayaan niyo po kaming magbigyan ng limang minuto. Parang mailatag namin kung paano namin maipipresenta at ang basihan namin sa pagpresenta ng aming ebidensya.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Your Honor, may I respond?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: The Presiding Officer's Rule.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Although indeed we will interpret the rules liberally, and although indeed this is a sui generis proceeding, neither will we allow any dilatory moves and or tactics, and I will bind and hold you to your five minutes, Honorable Defensor. Absolutely, Your Honor. Clockit. We will afford the same opportunity to the Counsel for Respondent when their turn arrives.
Rep. Lorenz R. Defensor: Thank you, Your Honor. May I proceed, Your Honor?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: You may proceed.
Rep. Lorenz R. Defensor: Honorable Senator Judges, Noong ikadalawamput dalawa ng hunyo, 2026, nagulat at nagdalamhati ang buong bansa sa pamamaril sa isang paaralan sa Tacloban City na ikinasawi ng tatlong batang mag-aaral at ikinasugat ng marami pang iba. Ang mga salarin, Mga minor de edad, sa kabila ng kanilang murang edad, agad na pumilos ang mga otoridad upang ipatubad ang mga umiiral na batas. Ang mensahe ay malinaw. Ang pag-igiging bata ay hindi nangangahulugang walang pananagutan. Ang pananagutan ay umiiral pagamat iba ang paraan ng pagpapatupad nito sa ilalim ng batas. Kamakailan, Isang pasahero ang inaresto sa airport at kinasuhan matapos itong magbiro na may bomba sa kanyang bagahe dahil mahigpit
Rep. Lorenz R. Defensor: na
Rep. Lorenz R. Defensor: ipinapatupad ng mga otoridad ang patakarang Zero Tolerance Policy sa anumang pagbabanggit ng bomba o anumang pampasabok. Sa isang hiwalay na pangyayari noong Mayo 2020, isang public school teacher ang inaresto Pinusasan at kinasuhan ng NBI sa Zambales matapos magbiro na magbibigay ng pabuya sa sino mang papatay sa Presidente ng Republika. Ano ang prinsipyo dito? Ang pananagutan ay pinapairal sa lahat, bata man o matanda, nasa laylayan man o nasa katungkulan. The prosecution comes before you today to present evidence for Article 4. Establishing that Vice President Sara Zimmerman Duterte committed acts that betrayed the public trust, committed culpable violation of the Constitution, committed high crimes in publicly admitting through a live broadcast that she contracted someone to assassinate the President, the First Lady, and the former House Speaker. We acknowledge the burden of this trial on the senator judges as well as the Filipino people. But it is a duty that we must discharge together, lest the public come to believe that threatening public officials and fostering a culture of impunity are conduct that may be tolerated or condoned. Especially coming from the second highest official of the land. Ang mga kilos at salita ng vicepresidente ay hindi dapat ituring na simpleng krimen sa ilalim ng batas, kundi tuwirang paglabag sa saligang batas. Kaya ang paglilitis na ito ay mahalagang mekanismong itinakda upang tiyakin na ang kapangyarihan ay laging may kaakibat na pananagutan. Accountability must apply to all or none at all. At the heart of this impeachment proceeding lies a fundamental question para sa ating lahat. Can we continue to entrust one of the highest constitutional offices to a public official who on multiple occasions purposely and willfully and repeatedly resorted to threats of violence against the very institutions The evidence presented in this article are not just derived from testimonies and authenticated documents, but from the Vice President's own words, own conduct, her very own public admissions. Her words were neither accidental nor taken out of context. They were uttered publicly with the intention to be taken seriously. Huwag kang mag-alala ma'am sa security ko kasi may kinausap na ako na tao. At sinabi ko sa kanya na kapag pinatay ako, patayin mo si BBM, si Lisa Marcos, si Martin Romaldez. No joke. No joke. What makes these threats especially sinister is that they do not come from an ordinary citizen but from the Vice President herself, an official who under the Constitution. The President of the Republic.
Rep. Lorenz R. Defensor: What values do we expect from those who occupy the highest office in the land? Delicadeza. Palabra de honor. Integrity and loyalty to your oath of office. These are not outdated ideals. They are the foundations of honorable public office. Maraming salamat po, your honors.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: The remarks of the gentlemen are duly noted. However, chair would like to inform and instruct the senator judges. That the statement and manifestation made by the Honorable Defensor should not in any way be taken as evidentiary because it was merely a manifestation cum introduction of the Fourth Article of Impeachment. Any evidence to be presented proving the Fourth Article of Impeachment should be done through a witness under oath, duly subscribed, and subjected to direct and cross-examination. Your Honor,
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: may I be allowed also to... Your Honor, we move to strike that opening statement. It's improper for trial. It is not evidentiary in nature. And it only provides conclusions of fact and law. Most of it is irrelevant. And fact of the matter is the prosecution should not present, should present evidence and not manifest in this improper manner.
Rep. Lorenz R. Defensor: May I be recognized, Your Honor?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: No need. Motion is denied. Let it remain in the records and as instructed by the Chair, for the Senator-Judges not to consider, deem, whatever statements were given by the Honorable Defensor as evidentiary in any way, shape, size, or form. Again, Counsel, call your first witness. Your
Rep. Lorenz R. Defensor: Honor, may I request permission to recognize Counsel for the panel of prosecutors. Atty. Virgil Ligutan To conduct the examination of our first witness, he will be under the direct supervision and control of
Rep. Lorenz R. Defensor: the
Rep. Lorenz R. Defensor: panel
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: of prosecutors.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Your
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Honor, may I register my continuing objection to the opening statement by the prosecution?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Well, I don't think he'll do it again, but nevertheless, so noted.
Rep. Lorenz R. Defensor: Thank you, Your Honor. May I request that Atty. Virgil D. Ligutan be recognized to conduct the examination of our first witness?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Atty. Virgil D.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Ligutan Mga kababayan, we call to the witness stand the first witness for the prosecution in the person of NBI Senior Agent John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Kindly bring the witness to the witness stand.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Please remain standing. Clerk of Court is instructed to kindly administer the oath to the witness.
Atty. Renato N. Bantug Jr.: Please raise your right hand. You, John Mark Calilung.
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: I, John Mark Calilung.
Atty. Renato N. Bantug Jr.: Do swear.
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: Do swear.
Atty. Renato N. Bantug Jr.: That the evidence you shall give
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: That the evidence I shall give
Atty. Renato N. Bantug Jr.: In the case now pending
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: In the case now pending
Atty. Renato N. Bantug Jr.: Between the Philippines and Vice President Sara Zimmerman Duterte
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: Between the Philippines and Vice President Sara Zimmerman Duterte
Atty. Renato N. Bantug Jr.: Shall be the truth
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: Shall be the truth
Atty. Renato N. Bantug Jr.: The whole truth
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: The whole truth
Atty. Renato N. Bantug Jr.: And nothing but the truth
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: And nothing but the truth. So help me God.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Thank you so much, Your Honors.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Your Honors, mga kababayan, the testimony of the first witness for the prosecution, NBI Senior Agent John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung, is offered to prove the following. Number one, si Agent John Mark Calilung ay isang Senior Agent of the National Bureau of Investigation. Number two, He is well-trained and experienced in the field of digital forensic examination, having undergone extensive training in the field, making him competent in identifying, preserving, collecting, and authenticating digital evidence. Pangatlo, si Agent Calilung ay bahagi NBI Cybercrime Division Team na inatasang mag-imbestiga sa mga pahayag at pagbabanta ng Vice Presidente Laban sa Pangulo ng Pilipinas Unang Ginang at dating Speaker ng House of Representatives sa isang online media briefing noong Nobyembre 23 taong 2024 pang-apat. Partikular.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Ito
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: ay nakatatak na sa kasaysayan ng ating bansa bilang unang pagkakataon ng isang bisipresidente ay nakipagkontrata Sa isang mamamatay tao upang patayin, no less than, the President of the Republic of the Philippines.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Panglima.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Your Honor, may I object? Is this a speech or an offer? Your
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Honor, please, with all the respect to counsel, it should not be a... May I
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: register my continuing objection?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: There is no proper ground. This is offer of testimony. Please, please hold your horses. Number 5. The public statements and threats of the Vice President were publicly livestreamed and captured on video. Number 6. Agent Calilung is the designated agent on case for the investigation. Number 7. As agents on case, Agent Calilung personally conducted and participated in the cybercrime and open-source investigation relating to the subject video and related digital recordings. Pangwalo sa
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: takbo ng open-source investigation na pag-alaman ng NBI na ang Vice Presidente
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: 9.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: In the course of the investigation, Agent Calilong duly identified Preserved, collected, and authenticated the subject video and other related digital recordings. At number 10, the last offer of testimony, Your Honors, Agent Calilung will testify on such other matters as may be relevant, material, incidental to the issues involved in this impeachment proceeding and will identify relevance. Atty. Ed material, documentary, and object, pieces of evidence. That is the offer of testimony of our first witness, Your Honor, please.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Your Honor, may we move for the exclusion of Agent Calilung for
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Being not previously attached to the Sebalha and Cabrera complaints, as well as exclusion on the ground that he was not included in the articles of impeachment transmitted to the Senate Impeachment Court.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Can I respond to that, Your Honor, please? Counsel for Prosecutor Meduso. Mga kababayan, in this stage of the proceedings, the prosecution is about to present a witness. And the defense is invoking the fact that this witness is not listed as one of the witnesses in the Sabalia complaint. The Sabalia complaint already lived its natural life. Your Honor, this is the impeachment proceeding of the articles of impeachment filed by the House of Representatives. Sabalia et al. is done. That should not be... A proper objection, Your Honor, please. As to the number two, I think the good counsel mentioned that it is not part, this witness is not part of the articles of impeachment.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Your Honor, please. I have been practicing for quite some time. I don't see that. Your
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Honor, may I allow to reply also?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Can I finish? It's not a ground. And in fact, Your Honor, please, to settle the matter, this witness is listed in the pretrial order. The issue is settled. The issue is passé. No ground for objection. Let me proceed, Your Honor. Of
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: course not, Your Honor. There were no rulings. Counsel
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: and correspondent is recognized for a final rebuttal on this issue before the chair will issue a ruling.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Your Honor, there were no rulings on the pretrial order on exclusion of witnesses. We have a current petition with the Supreme Court questioning the very actions of the prosecution. To allow the presentation of evidence that were not attached to the Ceballia or Cabrera Implementation Complaints would allow the House of Representatives and the Prosecution to circumvent the very procedural abuse condemned in Stonehill v. Jocno and allow the violation of the Respondent's constitutional rights as held in Duterte v. House of Representatives. Your Honor, the Prosecution says the Ceballia complaints has have lived and they died their natural deaths. However, Your Honor, this precisely does not cure what the prosecution did. This does not cure the violation of the rights of my client.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: If I may, Your Honor, please. The
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Chair will make its ruling.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: The motion to exclude by the Council for Respondent is hereby denied. Chair cites Enrile v. Sandigan Bayan, which states that The prosecutors may add or rely on evidence during pretrial even if the evidence is not stated in the complaint or articles because only a summary is required to be stated in the articles of impeachment in this case and or complaint and not a complete list of the prosecution's evidence and or witnesses. The court in general will not shackle the prosecution by limiting it to the evidence mentioned in the information and or the articles especially when it is mentioned. In the pre-trial brief, not only order, but brief, of the Council for Persecutors. But in relation to this witness, even if you will do cross, you can register your continuing objection. Council for Responding.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: We are registering it, Your Honor, please.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: So noted.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Counsel for the Prosecution may proceed.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Thank you so much, Your Honor. John Mark Calilung.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Your
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Honor, may I register my objections to the purposes?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: I think the purposes must be specified. What are your objections? On what grounds? May I be allowed? You
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: may comment on the offer of the testimony of this witness for the record.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Your Honor, for the purpose number three, this is a conclusion of fact and law. For the fourth purpose, it is also a conclusion of fact and law. And the eighth purpose, it is a conclusion
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: of fact and law.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Yes, Senator Judge Cayetano. Pia.
Sen. Pia S. Cayetano: I would just like the defense when you say item number three. Can you repeat what it is? Because I'm trying to follow exactly what your objection is. So either you say it or he repeats it so we can follow.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: I was about to do that actually.
Sen. Pia S. Cayetano: Thank you.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Item number three in the offer of this witness. Is that the NBI agent being presented is part of its cybercrime unit that investigated this matter?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: That's what you're referring to as a conclusion of law counsel?
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Perhaps number 4? Number 4, Your Honor. Yes, not number 3.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: So number 4 and what else?
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Number 8, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Number 8 on other threats other than the video mentioned in the press briefing, yes?
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Yes, Your Honor.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Correct, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Would that be all?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Yes, Your Honor. We will not reply to that, Your Honor, please.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Yes, please.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: May I continue, Your Honor, please?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: You may
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: continue to present your first witness, Counsel.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Thank you so much, Mr. Calilung. Reminder, nakikinig yung taong bayan, pakilakasan ng boses. Okay? Okay.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Mr. Witness, maaari bang sabihin mo ano yung pangalan, edad, at other personal circumstances?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: I am Senior Agent John Mark Calilung. Filipino citizen, 31 years old, with office address at NBI Phil Inves, Cyber Zone Bay City, Makapagal Boulevard, Pasay City, Sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: And Mr. Witness, reminder you may answer in Filipino or Tagalog or Filipino or English, okay? Mr. Witness, what is your occupation, if any?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: Currently, nasa National Bureau of Investigation po ako. I'm an agent since 2021 and was recently assigned at Cyber Investigation and Assessment Center in April 2026.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Okay, you said that you have been an agent of the NBI since 2021 pero you were recently assigned to the Cybercrime Investigation and Assessment Center of the NBI. Ano ba yung position mo before you were assigned to the Cybercrime Investigation and Assessment Center kung meron man?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: In 2022, I was assigned at Digital Forensic Laboratory Division and in 2024 in Cybercrime Division, Sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Okay. Now, you said that you were assigned to the Digital Forensics Laboratory Division in 2022. Now, yung tanong, ano ba yung mga naging primary?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: In
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: digital forensics, my primary duties is to identify, preserve, collect, analyze, and present digital evidence in court, sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Now, kung alam mo, ano ba yung naging trainings in that division?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: I have undergone computer hacking forensic investigation training, mobile forensics, computer forensics, and photo and video authentication training, sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Okay, so the last part of your answer, Mr. Witness, you mentioned that you were trained, na sinasabi mo, into photo... And video authentication. Now, specifically now, ano ba yung naging trainings in that regard? Photo and video authentication. Kung meron man.
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: I was trained for two weeks intensive training in July 2022 by MaxCore Intervention, sir, in digital forensic.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Now, sabi mo, ano nga ba yun? Two weeks of intensive training. Yung tanong, Mr. Witness. Specifically, What happened in that, you said, two weeks of intensive training?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: I was trained to perform digital forensic examination, sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Now, Mr. Witness, you tell the public, what is the objective, if any? What is the objective, if any, if you know, of that digital forensic examination that you said you were trained to do?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: To present digital evidence, sir, admissible in court, na ginawa ko na po multiple times.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: You appeared in court multiple times. Specifically, how many times?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: At least 30 times, sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: And for how long have you been practicing digital forensic examination? Two years, sir. For two years. Now, let's go back, Mr. Witness. You mentioned that you were an agent of the NBI Cybercrime Division in 2024. Now... What were your primary duties and functions as an agent of that cybercrime division?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: To investigate cases in violation to the cybercrime law, sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Cybercrime law. Now, Mr. Witness, you are testifying in this impeachment case proceeding trial against the vice president, the respondent in this case. Do you know the respondent in this case?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: Yes, sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: And why do you know the respondent in this case?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: Because she is the vice president and my team conducted an investigation involving her, sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: So aside from being the vice president, your team, you said, investigated the vice president. The question now is, what was this investigation if you know?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: It's an investigation on the statement uttered by the Vice President during an online press conference briefing dated November 23, 2024.
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: So,
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: statements uttered by the Vice President in an online livestream press conference held on November 23, 2024. Now, yung tanong, ano ba yung naging participation mo, Mr. Witness, kung meron man? I am the agent on case of the investigation, Sir. Now, sinabi mo ikaw yung agent on case. Now, you tell the court, you tell the public, ano ba yung pagiging ahente on the case? Ano bang ibig sabihin yan kung alam mo?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: It means that I gathered evidence necessary for the investigation, sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Okay. You mentioned you gathered evidence. Now, you tell us, what do you mean kung meron man, tsaka kung alam mo, ano bang ibig sabihin when you quote?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: It
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: means that I viewed, identified, preserved, collected, and authenticated digital evidence in the course of the investigation, sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Okay. Now, you mentioned that you viewed, identified, preserved, collected, authenticated, sinasabi mo mga pieces of evidence that you found in the course of your investigation. Tama ba?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Now,
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Mr. Witness, yung tanong is ano ba yung mga ebidensya na nakalap ng inyong team?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: One of the pieces of evidence that we gathered during our investigation is the video of the November 23, 2024 online press conference held by the Office of the Vice President which was posted on the Facebook page of Harry Roque, sir. Facebook page of whom? Harry Roque, sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Harry Roque. Okay. Yes, sir. Mr. Witness, sinabi mo, you gathered. And then sinabi mo kanina, pag sinabing gathered evidence, sinabi mo, you viewed, identified, preserved, collected, and authenticated. Preserved, collected, and authenticated. You mentioned the term preserved, correct? Mr. Witness, yung tanong now is, ano ba ang ibig sabihin when you, quote, Preserved and quote the evidence.
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: It means that I ensure that the evidence will be accessible at any time, sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Okay now, let's go to this video you mentioned. The video, ang sinasabi mo, yung isang online media briefing ng Vice President noong November 23, 2024. Ano ba yung mga hakbang kung meron man na ginawa niyo to preserve that video?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: The NBI Cybercrime Division. Through me, initiated a preservation request po kay Meta.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Okay, you initiated a preservation request to Meta. Now, sinabi mo kanina na livestream yung subject video sa isang Facebook page, Facebook page ng isang Harry Roque, diba? Now, yung tanong, why is it that your request was made to Meta?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: Si
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: Meta po kasi yung parent company po ng Facebook. At under po ng meta si Facebook, si Instagram, saka si WhatsApp. All requests on that platform will go to meta po. Alright.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Now, Mr. Witness, what proof, if any, do you have that you initiated a preservation request to meta in order to preserve the subject video?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: I have a screenshot of the preservation request. A screenshot of the webpage wherein I made the preservation request, sir. Who took the screenshot? I did, sir, and I used my laptop. Anong ginawa mo sa screenshot kung meron man pagkatapos diyan? I first saved po yung electronic copy sa laptop ko, then printed it.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Where is this print out of the screenshot now?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: Sinubmit ko po sa Committee on Justice of House of Representatives.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Your Honor, with the Court's indulgence, may I move that this representation be assisted by a co-counsel for the sole reason of... Facilitating the presentation of the documents to the witness for that reason alone.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Sa Tagalog, siya mag-aabot? Yes, Your Honor. Siya po yung mag-aabot ng mga dokumento na amin pong ipapakita for the witness to identify po.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Counsel may proceed.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Thank
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: you so much. Assisted by Atty. Stephen Magalyon. Now, if this printout is shown to you, Will you be able to identify the same?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: Yes, sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Now, we invite the defense to also peruse the document.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Your Honor, may I request that one of our councils be allowed to peruse the document?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Yes, one of the councils for respondent may look at the document being presented to the witness.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: May I continue, Your Honor, please?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Thank you. Now, I'm showing you.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Defense, can we... Can we give the document to the witness, please? Your Honor, the document must be presented to the witness. Give them some time to look at it, but is this one of the documents pre-marked?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Yes, Your Honor, please.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: For the record, can you state the pre-marking of this document just so that we can catch up?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Much obliged, Your Honor, please. That would be P-Roman numeral 4-7 for the prosecution, Your Honor, please.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Noted. Your Honor, may I manifest for the record that this is not a certified true copy.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Noted. Your Honor, can I respond to that, Your Honor, please? This is an electronic copy. The rules on electronic evidence says a printed version of an electronic copy is an original. Your Honor, please.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Counsel for the Prosecutor, Counsel for Responder did not object. He just simply made an observation regarding the document. So you may proceed as soon as the document is returned to
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: the witness. Thank you so much, Your Honor, please.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: What relation?
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Be sure we
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: test. Are we ready?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: What relation, if any, does these documents have with the printout of the screenshot that you mentioned?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: This is the copy of the printout that was submitted to the Committee on Justice, sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Okay. Your Honor, please may I proceed with the next question, please? Question. Mr. Witness, how fateful, if at all, is this printout from the actual screenshots?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: The printout accurately reflects the screenshots, sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: How do you know now that this printout accurately reflects the screenshot?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: I compared the printout with the screenshot and with the webpage of my preservation and found that the contents are identical, sir. Thank you so much. Now, Mr.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Witness, ano ba ang nangyari kung meron man? At kung alam mo, after you made...
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: After you made the preservation to request to META in relation to the investigation you did on the vice president.
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: META acknowledge our preservation request, sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Your Honor, please. The exhibits as they come, as they are identified by the witness, are also simultaneously being presented on the screen, Your Honor, please.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Okay. You said that META acknowledge the preservation request, correct? Yes, sir. Now, yung tanong ngayon, ano bang puro iba mo? Kung meron man, that's in fact, Meta acknowledged the request.
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: I have a screenshot of the acknowledgement of Meta email acknowledgement.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Now, who took the screenshot?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: I did, sir, and I used my laptop.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: What did you do with the screenshot kung meron man?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: Sinip ko muna po yung electronic copy ng screenshot sa laptop ko and printed it.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Where is the printout of the screenshot?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: I submitted to the Committee on Justice of the House of Representatives.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Now, if the printout of the screenshot will be shown to you, will you be able to identify the same?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: Yes, sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Now, we are now in the process of showing you the printout of a screenshot of a response or reply of the Meta that is previously marked as Exhibit P-Roman numeral 4-8 for the prosecution.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Your Honor, may I have time to produce?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Kindly show the document to one of the counsels for the respondent.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Your Honor, we note that Exhibit P-IV-8 is not an original or certified true copy, and we object to the introduction of this and the identification of this.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: What does counsel for the prosecution say?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Again, I reiterate: if it is a printout of an electronic document, the rules are clear that that is an original.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Your Honor, if you look at it, on the bottom left-hand portion there is a mark, ‘certified true copy.’ This certified true copy would not have appeared in any correspondence with noreply@records.facebook.com.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: So
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: it is not a printout. It's not an original. It would not reflect what accurately was printed out or appeared on the screen. What
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: does counsel for the prosecutor say?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Two points, your honor, please. Settled now, 2019. Assuming that the counsel is correct. Photocopy now is considered as unregional, Your Honor, please. And number two, Your Honor, please. With all respect, presentation of evidence, objection to the admissibility of object and documentary evidence happens when the documents are formally offered in evidence. We are just in the process, Your Honor, please, of presenting this evidence. So therefore, the defense may object thereto. When we formally offer the exhibition, and that's not happening yet.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Your Honor, my—
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: As a last point, Counsel for Respondents, before the Chair makes a ruling.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Your
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Honor, true that photocopies are now considered originals. However, the photocopy must be an accurate and exact reproduction of that original or that printout. This, Your Honor, may I read it for the record?
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: In the bottom left-hand copy, it says, certified true copy, NBI-Cybercrime, signed Safira T., date 4-10-26.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Is
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: counsel for the prosecution telling us now that this marking came from Meta, the email of Meta, of Facebook? Can
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: you respond, counsel, before the chair makes a ruling? I'm interested to hear your response as well.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: I'm so sorry. Could you repeat the question, please?
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: It was rhetorical, Your Honor. He did not answer.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: He was basically questioning the fact that if it indeed came from Meta and is a computer printout, why the need for someone to certify it as a true copy?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: I do recall, Your Honor, please, that was submitted to the Committee on Justice. Along the way, there was a need to certify that, Your Honor, please. But be that as it may, certification of a printout of an electronic document is not even necessary, Your Honor, please.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: The objection of the counsel-forrespondent is overruled. Counsel may proceed.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Thank you so much, Your Honor, please.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: He may raise his objection at the proper time. Informal offer is made of documentary evidence, and any correction may be made thereafter. Or rather, before that, by the counsel for the prosecutors. Please proceed. Thank
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: you so much. Mr. Witness, you mentioned that Meta, you said, acknowledged the preservation requests. Now, sorry, Your Honor, please. I recall the last question. I have to proceed to presentation of the documents. Now, Mr. Witness, if this print out. Now that the screenshot of Meta's reply is shown to you, will you be able to identify the same?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: Yes, sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Now, what relation, if any, does that document have with the printout that you mentioned earlier?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: This is the printout that I submitted, sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Now, Mr. Witness, Your Honor, please, again, as previously manifested.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: The document identified by the witness has been previously marked as Exhibit P-4-8 for the prosecution. How faithful, if at all, is this printout from the actual screenshot?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: The printout accurately reflects the screenshot, sir. And
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: how do you know that this printout accurately reflects the screenshot?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: I compared the screenshot with the printout and the email confirmation of Meta and found that the contents are identical, sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: That meta quote acknowledged, unquote, the preservation requests. Now, based on your experience, and if you know, what does it mean if the meta acknowledges a preservation request?
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Objection, Your Honor. He would be incompetent to say that.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Your Honor, please.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Counsel for the prosecution, what do you say?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Your Honor, please. This is an NBI agent that has been practicing digital forensics for two years, appearing in court for 30 times, and underwent trading for two weeks. No other person in this room is more competent to answer the question than this witness. Let the witness answer.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Nevertheless, Your Honor, he's incompetent. He is not from Meta. He doesn't know Meta procedures. The mere fact that he's an NBA agent doesn't make him competent. Can I reply to that, Your Honor, please?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Overruled. Chair will allow it. If the witness knows, he may reply. If he does not know, he should so admit also. Witness may answer.
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: It means that Meta have taken necessary action to preserve the evidence, sir, and assign a case number on it.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: So, took reasonable steps to preserve an assigned... A case number. Now, your question now is, after receiving this acknowledgement from META, what did you do, if there was any, in relation to the investigation you conducted on the statements of the Vice President?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: I further preserve the video and authenticate the same, sir. All
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: right, so you said...
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: With the permission of the Council for the Prosecutors. Witness, Mr. Witness. What do you mean by META assigned a case number to it? What does that exactly mean?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: It means that they have taken reasonable action. The case number is for monitoring because it's multiple requests from different investigations. The case number is for specific requests.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: So if you have
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: requested from META to preserve a digital footprint or data, they will put a case number?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: Yes,
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: sir.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: All the requests that will be preserved today will be placed under the case number of those requests?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: No, the case number will be per request.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: So each request will have a separate case number from Meta?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: Yes, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: And the case number for this one would be what?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: 911-6154, Your Honor. Where is
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: that written?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: Your case number is at the upper part, Your Honor. 911
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: -6154?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: Yes, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: You may proceed, Counsel.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Thank you. Thank
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: you so much. Mr. Witness, you said that you proceeded to further preserve and authenticate the subject video. Now, let's go to that proceeded to further evidence. What does it entail, if any, and if you know?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: It means that I further preserve it using a screen recording, open source broadcast software studio, OBS. I screen record what appears on my screen, the video The online livestream November 23, 2024 from beginning to end including its URL.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Okay. Now, what about authenticating the video? What does that mean if you know?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: After screen recording, there's an output video. I compared the output video with the November 23, 2024 video and ensured that the contents are identical. After ensuring that the contents are identical, I now generated a hash value calculation on the video to ensure that the video won't be tampered until presented in court, sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Mr. Witness, ano ba yung prueba mo kung meron man that you authenticated the subject video?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: I have executed an affidavit of authentication of digital evidence dated January 30, 2025, sir. Okay,
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: now. If the Affidavit of Authentication of Digital Evidence dated January 30, 2025 will be shown to you, will you be able to identify the same?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: Yes, sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Now in the process or the prosecution is in the process of confronting the witness with a document that is previously marked as Exhibit P-Roman numeral 4-9 and series constituting of 29 pages including the attachments, Your Honor. Please, the defense is invited to peruse the documents.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Your Honor,
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: we object to the introduction of this affidavit of authentication. This is not an original copy of his affidavit. This is not electronic evidence. And if you look at the affidavit even the appendages which are which supposedly consist of usbs and uh cd there's no usb there's no cd uh and even the signatures are not are not wet signatures your honor
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: We will not comment to that, subject to the proper response to that when the time comes in the formal offer of exhibit, Your Honor, please.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: The objection of the counsel for respondent is noted as to the admissibility of the offered document. However, as correctly pointed out by counsel for the prosecution, the proper time to object to the same and for the court to rule on it would be During formal offer, once the prosecution has already rested its case. Thank you
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: so much. Mr. Witness, what relation, if any, does that document have with the affidavit that you mentioned?
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Your
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Honor,
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: may I just make a quick manifestation?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Counsel for the respondent. Yes, you may, sir.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Your
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Honor, during pretrial, The parties got together and agreed that originals of the documents that were to be marked will be presented during trial. We agreed
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: to
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: expedite the proceedings. And now what is happening is photocopies of documents that we want to peruse and see are being presented. So we object to this, Your Honor. If I may, can I reply?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Sorry, I'm so sorry. The
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: manifestation of the counsel for respondent is Julie Noten.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Thank you so much, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Please proceed, counsel, for the prosecution.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: On page 3 of the Affidavit of Authentication of Digital Evidence, may makikita diyan yung isang firma sa ibabaw ng pangalang John Mark Calilung. Do you see it? Yes, sir. Yung tanong now is whose signature is that if you know?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: This is my signature, sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Your Honor, at this juncture, Your Honor, please, despite the prosecution's understanding that a photocopy is now the original, is now considered as an original, but to address the concerns of the defense, Your Honor, please, I move that we be allowed to present the original. The original of the documents that the witness was confronted with is a certified true copy of the affidavit of authentication, Your Honor, please.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Counsel may proceed.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Okay. Now, you mentioned, so I will go back. Now, Mr.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Without prejudice to the counsel for respondent viewing the same with respect to its certification.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Affidavit of Authentication of Digital Evidence dated January 30, 2025. Now,
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: we
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: are confronting you now with a certified true copy of the same document.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: After perusing the same, you have to tell us what relation, if any, do the documents before you have with the documents. Affidavit of Authentication of Digital Evidence that you mentioned.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Yes, Counsel for Respondent.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: We'll finish perusing, Your Honor.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Let's put it properly, secretly, secretly, secretly. Let's put it properly, secretly, secretly, secretly. Let's put it properly, secretly, secretly,
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: secretly.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Your Honor, for... Yes, counsel
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: for the respondent.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Thank you, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: You may proceed, sir, for your comments.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Sir, for, Your Honor, for P-I, P-4-9H.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Your Honor, there is a CD in the original.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Next page.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Next
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: page.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Next page. Next page. Spot the difference. Your Honor, for B -4-9H, in the original, there's a marking. November 23. And in the photocopy, it is only a photocopy of the CD, Your Honor. So there's a difference.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Noted?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: You
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: can
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: reply to that, Your Honor, please.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Counsel, let's get all of his comments first.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: The page after is already a USB. Your
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Honor, the page after in the original is a USB. Which is Annex E-1 with markings October 18, 2024 video CLPPS 182.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: However,
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: in the photocopy, there is no such thing.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: So the order is no longer the same moving forward, Your Honor.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Even
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: in that very same one, which I assume is P-4-9K does not have any date marking, Your Honor. So it is not the same document. It's not faithful reproduction of anything, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: The photocopy is not a faithful reproduction of the certified true copy. That's what you're stating.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Yes, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: What does the counsel for the prosecution say?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Your Honor, counter-manifestation that the documents that the defense are producing have been identified by the very person who authenticated and who executed that exhibit. So, Your Honor, please remove that the comments of the defense be noted, Your Honor, please.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Your Honor, that's irrelevant. What we're saying is that this is not the copy mark. It is not the... The same as the original, which he says is the same thing which is identified. What he's saying is off tangent. What he identified earlier, which is the marked copy, which is the copy marked during pretrial, is not the same document as they are passing on as an original. Your Honor, this is the issue here. Counsel for
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Respondent, that is a proper subject matter too for your cross to point, if at all, the distinction and difference between the two copies. Which counsel for the prosecution can use as a subject matter for his redirect?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Thank you, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Because you can confront the witness with respect to the certified true copy that is different from what he identified earlier, impugning, if at all, his credibility as a witness in this case. Thank you so much. So
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: we note the comments and observations of the counsel for the respondent. I got lost. So it's being reviewed and has not yet been given to the witness, right?
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Your Honor, may I just register our continuing objection?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: So noted and so registered.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Thank you
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: so much.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Can we proceed?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Before we proceed, the presiding officer was not there during pretrial. As manifested by the counsel correspondent, was there indeed such an agreement that the originals will be presented during the trial?
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Yes,
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Your Honor. By both parties. Can the counsel for the prosecutors also confirm that?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Your Honor, please. We do not confirm. I conferred with my team, the team who actually participated in the marking for Article 4. Your Honor, please. Be that as it may, Your Honor, please, we would like to put into record certain
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: realities
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: of the law. A photocopy is now considered as an original. 2019 amendments in the Rules of Evidence. Number two, Your Honor, please. This is the person who authenticated the documents. So there's no other person who is competent to testify as to the veracity of these documents other than the witness. Your Honor, please. So you do not confirm such
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: an agreement during pretrial?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: We do not confirm that, Your Honor, please.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Chair would like to advise the parties. The court understands the exceptions to the original document rule and will so implement the rules in that regard. However, if it does not fall under the original document rule exceptions, Then to save on the court's time, the party presenting the document should present the original during trial to evade what we are seeing now. Perhaps the next time you present a witness, counsel for the prosecutors and counsel for respondents. We
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: will, Your Honor. We appreciate that, Your Honor. Please, we understand that would be for the next presentation. For the next one. Please proceed. Thank you so much. Are we done now? We move, Your Honor, please, that the—
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Your Honor, may I request that he not also address me directly?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: So ordered, so instructed. Kindly address all of your queries and statements to the Presiding Officer and use the third person when referring to your fellow counsel for the other party.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Much obliged, Your Honor, please. We move, Your Honor, please, that the marking— In the affidavit of authentication of digital evidence that was previously identified by the witness in photocopy, the markings of the same be transposed to the documents that this witness is being confronted with at present. We
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: object to this, Your Honor. This is precisely our earlier objection. They are marking a new document. That's why they're asking that it be marked again, which defeats the very purpose of our pre-trial.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: So, the hearing will proceed, Your Honor, please. I will withdraw that motion. We will stand by the presentation, the photocopy, allowed by the rules, and identified by the witness who actually executed the affidavit. May proceed, Your Honor, please. I
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: hope this satisfies, Counsel for Respondent. You may proceed, Sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Thank you so much, Your Honor. Now, Mr. Witness, on page 3, sa pahit ng… 3. Of the Affidavit of Authentication of Digital Evidence, may makikitang isang pirma sa ibabaw ng pangalang Agent John Mark Calilung. Now, yung tanong, kaninong pirma ba ito kung alam mo? Pirma ko po, Sir. Now, sa page 4 ng nasabing Affidavit of Authentication of Digital Evidence, may makikita din na isang pirma sa ibabaw ng pangalang Attorney Jeremy C. Lotok. Now, which signature is this, if you know?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: This is the signature of Atty. Lotok. Now, how do you know that it is the signature of Atty. Lotok?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: I saw that he signed the document.
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: There are documents that I saw and enacted upon bearing his signature, so I am familiar with it.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Thank you so much, Your Honor. Please, we proceed, Mr. Witness. Now, what action did you perform, if any, After you authenticated the subject video in relation to the investigation you conducted on the statements of the vice presidents.
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: I first saved the video on my laptop and saved a copy of the video on a DVD and a flash drive.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Okay, now you mentioned that you saved a copy. In a flash drive. Mr. Witness, kung yung flash drive ipapakita sa'yo, will you be able to identify the same? Objection,
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Your Honor. We object.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: What is the objection of the counsel?
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: The
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: document identified by the witness was the photocopy. And there's no flash drive, CD, or anything appended upon that. So there's nothing. No foundation for this question. I
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: have to reply to that, Your Honor, please. This is a non -issue. I asked the witness what did he do after saving the video and he said he saved it in a flash drive without referring to any document attached to the affidavit of authentication. Basis is laid, Your Honor, please. This is a non-issue. We may proceed, Your Honor, please. Your Honor,
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: may I respond?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Counsel for the respondent.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: This is not a surprise. This was flash drives, several flash drives were pre-marked during the pre-trial. I
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: believe
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: seven on the part of the prosecution and several on the part of the respondent too. But you may proceed, sir.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Your Honor, that is not my objection. My objection is the very basis upon which the witness introduced this flash drive was the affidavit. The affidavit. And there was no affidavit upon the, there was no attachment upon the affidavit which they introduced. So the very questions that he has does not, do not have any foundation.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Counsel for the prosecution, before the presiding officer makes a ruling.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Ako yung magiging ano na, parang sirang ano. I just said that this witness said That he saved a copy of that video in a flash drive. So the logical question now is to ask him if this flash drive is presented to him, is he able to explain and or identify the same? I don't see any proper basis for an objection to that, Your Honor, please.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Presenting officer will make a ruling. Objection is overruled. The prosecution, counsel for the prosecution is trying to comply with the requirements enunciated by the Supreme Court insofar as such pieces of evidence is concerned. Number one, establishing its origin. Number two, to trace the chain of custody insofar as the transfer to a storage device is concerned. And finally, how it reached this court. So the objection is overruled.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Thank you so much. Now, Mr. Witness, Atty. Bagalyon, please confront the witness with a flash drive.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Mr. Witness, I'm now showing a flash drive that is previously marked as Exhibit P-Roman numeral 4-10A containing the subject video that is previously marked as Exhibit P-4-10 for the prosecution. Question. What relation, if any, does this flash drive have with the one you mentioned?
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: May I know if this was appended upon any document?
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Thank you, Your Honor. May I know if this was appended upon any document?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: The answer is no, I presume.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: The basis, if at all, counsel for the respondent is the testimony of the witness.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: When asked again to establish not only the origin but also how he transferred it to a storage device and if at all how it reached this court. So share replies and if that is an objection overrules the same. Witness may answer.
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: Permission to unseal the flash drive.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: You may do so, sir.
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: Thank you, Your Honor.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Your Honor, the witness manifestation is now in the process of unsealing. The object evidence.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Witness will please answer.
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: This is the flash drive where I saved the recording, sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Now, Your Honor, please. At this juncture, we are about to confront the witness with the video contained in the flash drive. Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Kindly let the counsel for the prosecution finish. Yes,
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Yes, Your Honor. Thank you so much. And in the interest of time, Your Honor, please, we move that we allow Atty. Magallon to proceed to the technical booth to facilitate, Your Honor, please, the playing of the video when the time comes.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Your Honor, may we know how long the video is?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: We will arrive to that, Your Honor, please.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: No, I'm also curious. For us to know, how long is this particular video, namely Exhibit P-IV-10A? How many minutes or seconds would this be exactly?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: The video is two hours, 26 minutes, and 10 seconds. But wait, Your Honor, please. We will aid the court in this regard. We will not be showing the entire two-hour video, Your Honor, please. We will be presenting the relevant portions of the video, Your Honor, please, sanctioned by the rules and subject to the defense doing whatever they want with the remainder of the video, Your Honor, please.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: So what will you play exactly, counsel? How many minutes or seconds?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: We counted. It's two minutes and exactly 18 seconds, Your Honor, please—two minutes and 18 seconds of a two-hour, 26-minute-and-10-second video, Your Honor, please.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Counsel for respondent.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: We object. Your Honor, based on the rules, part of a video documentary must be presented, Your Honor.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: I'm sorry,
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: counsel?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: counsel? I did not get what you said.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Your Honor, under Rule 132, when part of a transaction writing a record given in evidence, the remainder must be shown. When part of an act, declaration, conversation, writing, or record is given in evidence by one party, the whole of the same subject may be inquired into. When a detached act, declaration, conversation, writing, or record is given in evidence, any other act, declaration, conversation, or record necessary to its understanding must be given into evidence. Your Honor, we request that the entire video be played.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Your
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Honor, can I respond to that, Your Honor, please? Can I respond to that?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: What does the counsel for the prosecution say before the chair makes a ruling?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Your Honor, please, we don't want to put the defense on the spot, but that is a misreading of the rules.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Your Honor, please. Council cited Rule 132, Section 17. With all respect to the defense, that doesn't serve your interest. It serves the interest of the prosecution. May I explain? Reason. If we read Section 17 of Rule 132, it says, When part of transaction writing a record given in evidence, the remainder is admissible. When parts of an act's declaration, conversation, writing a record, When part is given by one party, and in this case that is the prosecution, the whole of the same may be inquired into by the other side. Meaning, it's simple. This rule, Section 17, Rule 132, allows exactly the prosecution to present a two-minute portion of a two-hour video subject to the defense, the presentation of the remainder of the statement. Be that as it may, Your Honor, please, the rules are clear. Number two, we invoke, Your Honor, please, the ruling that it is for the prosecution to decide what to present, when to present, how to present. And whether to present at all. Be that as it may, Your Honor, please, the defense will not be prejudiced exactly because when the time comes for the defense to present their evidence, they can present the remainder of that two-hour video. What we are saying, Your Honor, please, for the interest of time, for the prosecution's presentation of evidence, we deem that only a two-minute portion of that two-hour video is relevant at this point in time, Your Honor, please. We move for a ruling. Your Honor, if I may respond.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: As the last response, counsel for the respondent.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Your Honor, the prosecution cannot be allowed to present a small, a truncated part of a whole 2R26 minute video. That will not provide the context necessary for the understanding of what occurred during that night on November 23, and also not allow the proper identification by this witness.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Your Honor, sorry, I will not even reply to that, Your Honor, please.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Chair would like to ask, who did the edit? From the, how many hours? Two hours? No.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Your Honor, please, if I may, can I
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: reply to that?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: From
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: the total, who did the edit? Did the witness? Was the witness the one who did the edit? Or was it already the prosecution?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Your Honor, there is no editing done.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: There is no editing done.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Who got that sorter person?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: No, Your Honor, please. What we are presenting are portions of the entire to our video. And this witness, I think, will be able to identify the specific timestamps of that preserved, not edited portion. If I may repeat you all please, we are not presenting any edited portions, but only snippets. PORTIONS OF THE TWO-HOUR VIDEO AND THIS WITNESS, I SUPPOSE, WILL BE ABLE TO IDENTIFY WHICH SPECIFIC PORTIONS THAT HE WOULD LIKE THE COURT TO VIEW AT THIS POINT.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Yes. The two or so minutes. Would that
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: be correct? That is a very good observation. I agree 100% Your Honor, please.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Your Honor, the prosecution cannot be allowed to do this because the entire video will show the context upon which the utterances were made.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: That is a matter for the counsel for respondent to do and present during their time because I believe the counsel for respondent also identified and marked. If I'm not mistaken, the same video for over two and a half hours. It can do so during its time to present its evidence in chief. The objection is overruled. Counsel is instructed to go to the booth accompanied by a counsel from the respondent in order to make sure that indeed the USB identified by the witness is the same USB that will be played in the tech booth of the Senate.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Okay.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: While they're doing that, may I propound the next question or the other, please?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Yes, counsel. You may proceed. Mr. Witness, John Mark, listen. Now, you mentioned kanina that you authenticated the subject video by recording the same through sinasabi mong open broadcaster software OBS. And then you compared the contents of the recording and the subject video. That's one. And you also said that you investigated. Certain statements made by the Vice Presidents on November 23, 2024. Yung tanong, no? What particular statements of the Vice President did the NBI deem proper to investigate?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: The statement of the Vice President where she uttered that she already talked to someone to kill the President, the First Lady, and the former Speaker of the House if something's happened to her.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Okay, now. The next question now, Mr. Witness, is
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: In what particular portion of the subject video did the respondent utter that she already contracted a person to
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: kill— Objection, Your Honor. Wait,
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: wait, wait. Allow the counsel to finish his question. I'm not yet done.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Relax.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: The First Lady and the former Speaker of the House. Objection, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: What? What is the objection of counsel-correspondent?
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Your Honor, no basis for the question, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Overall, witness may answer. May
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: I refer, sir, to my notes to identify the specific timestamp, sir?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Okay. The witness may do so if it is available to him. You may refer to your notes.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: While he is doing that, while the witness
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: is doing that,
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Senator Judge Alan Cayetano is recognized. You may proceed, sir. Your Honor,
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: may I question what notes
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: he is referring to? Counsel for Respondent, the Presiding Officer recognized Senator Judge Alan Cayetano. You may proceed, sir.
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: Just some thoughts, Presiding Officer. This is not yet an appeal from your ruling and may be a question to the Council of the Defense. Just to refresh our memory, Rule 132, Section 17. When part of a transaction writing or record given in evidence, the remainder admissible. When part of our act, declaration, conversation, writing or record is given in evidence by one party, the whole of the same subject may be inquired into by the other. And when a detached act, declaration, conversation, writing or record is given in evidence, any act, declaration,
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: Ito lang po ang tanong ko.
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: What did she say before or after? And I don't really want to go home today believing one thing based on a two-minute clip and then come back next week to watch the two-hour clip. I think most of us saw parts of the clip. Of course, I don't also feel like watching the two-hour. I don't even watch two-and-a-half-hour movies. Much less this, but I'm just putting this at the feet of the presiding officer and my colleagues na kung gagawin din naman natin eventually yung two and a half hours, mas gusto ba natin putulin muna ngayon at maiinisip tayo and then later on the two hours? Or can the two parties agree of the two and a half hours, which one yung may context? So I'm not criticizing the prosecution's motion. I see what you mean. May I ask that one question to the defense if they're going to ask, deciding officer?
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: For
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: the presiding officer, we cannot dictate nor predict what either counsel for the prosecution or respondent will do during the presentation of their evidence in chief. Even if they say yes to us now, actually they have every right to change their mind and not do so anymore.
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: But if they do answer now that they want it shown, May we consider, I mean if I'm the only one who wants to see it as a whole, then I will submit to everyone else. But if everyone else is saying we will eventually watch the whole of it, we might as well get it over and see the context of the whole video. Unless the two parties can agree. That they only want to look at 30 minutes or one hour. I don't know what context they're talking about. I'm just trying to expedite. Both parties,
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Senator Judge Alan Cayetano, marked the same video.
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: Yes. May I ask the... Which is over two hours. May I just ask the defense? Do they plan to ask us to watch the whole...
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Council for Defense will please reply to the question of Senator Judge Cayetano.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: First, Your Honor, precisely why we're asking to... Atty.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: J. Bag-ao.
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: Hindi naman nakalagay sa Section 17 when. And usually, at least for myself, if I have to watch 30 minutes and then may i-emphasize na 30 seconds, 2 minutes, 1 minute, pinapanood muna yung buo, and then saka papanoorin yung maikle na i-emphasize para walang pre-judgment. Kasi pag nauna yung portions na maliliit, and then saka mo lang sasabihin later on, ah, eto pala context neto. Medyo umiiba. But again, I'm only one of the 24, so I leave it to my colleagues. If we're going to have to watch it anyway, may I ask the presiding officer what the pleasure is. But since the rule doesn't say, personally, I'd rather watch the whole thing and get it over with than allow the prosecution to pick out the portions that quickly say. That goes into the center of the controversy or what they want to prove.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Without disagreeing with Senator Judge Cayetano, for the presiding officer it's just that I don't think the court should impose or dictate upon either party how they will present their evidence in chief.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Although it would save the court some time if they... But we can also waste a lot of time arguing about this instead of watching the two-minute video.
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: Mr. Presiding Officer, I'm not saying we dictate because there was an object and you ruled. You can change your ruling or we can appeal. But I'm saying I'm just one. So if everyone agrees na portion muna, I will submit to that. But if everyone else thinks na panorin na yung buo, then baka I can appeal your ruling without voting. So I'm just bringing up this issue for expediency, but I leave it up to what everyone else thinks about it.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Your Honor, if I may, we also move for the reconsideration of the earlier ruling of the honorable court.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Counsel cannot move for reconsideration of the ruling of the chair. Only a senator-judge
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: can do so. Your Honor, may we manifest that we intend to present the whole.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: During cross-examination, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Presiding officer declares a brief recess.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Thank you so much, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: May I invite the council for the parties to kindly situate themselves in their respective tables as well as the senator judges as we will resume in a minute.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: During the break, the presiding officer had a discussion with the senator judges including Senator Cayetano. The presiding officer would therefore like to make of record the following. Number one. Should the defense, should the counsel for the respondent rather, decide as it has manifested to present the entire video, this court shall allow it during the time for the respondent to present its evidence in chief. We will not interfere with how each party or either party presents their case. With a caveat that a portion of an entire video Being presented is not only to save on time but also to be able to support the allegations from the point of view of the prosecution insofar as their articles of impeachment is concerned. No need to say that the counsel for the respondent will also present the evidence that they deem best that will prove the innocence of the respondent in this case. Senator Judge Gaetano?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: The mic please of Senator Judge Cayetano.
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: Sir Presiding Officer, I submit and I think there's a consensus. May I ask just one question about authentication? You may proceed, sir. I want to be clarified with my indulgence to the prosecution and defense. Just to the witness, please correct me kasi hindi ako takey talaga dyan. So sabi mo pag in-authenticate mo, you get the video tapos may hash. Yes, Your Honor. So you get the hash, tapos you download the video, tama po ba?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: No, Your Honor. The video was screen-recorded, Your Honor. Okay,
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: so screen-recorded, then yung hash na nakuha mo?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: Yung hash value po is kinalkulate from the recorded po.
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: Okay, then you have to compare that with the original one, right? Yes,
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: Your Honor.
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: So the original one, yung hash niyan, nasa Facebook, tama ba?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: Yung hash po hindi po kinalkulate yung…
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: Is
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: there a possibility na iba yung hash ng Facebook for the same video sa hash nung sa'yo?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: Magkaiba po talaga. Magkaiba.
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: But how do you know when you authenticated, how do you know it's the same video?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: I manually compared, Your Honor.
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: Manually compared? Yes,
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: Your Honor.
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: But we don't know that unless we also manually compare.
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: Yes, Your Honor.
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: Thank you. I just want to clarify that and think about it more.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Noted and entered into the records. What is the pleasure of Senator Judge Villanueva?
Sen. Joel Villanueva: Mr. Presiding Officer, in relation to what Atty. Senator Judge Alan Cayetano mentioned. May I just be allowed to ask a clarificatory question in relation to that particular matter? Senator Judge
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Villanueva may do so. He has two minutes.
Sen. Joel Villanueva: Thank you. Mr. Witness, I was listening attentively earlier and you made mention that the livestream video was recorded using open broadcaster software or OBS. Just for the benefit of the court, could you briefly explain what OBS is and how it was used in the course of your investigation?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: It's an open source software na pwede po i-access ng kahit sino. So it's generally
Sen. Joel Villanueva: available
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: to
Sen. Joel Villanueva: the
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: public? Yes po. And ang purpose po niya is may two functions siya. It's live stream and screen recording po. And stream
Sen. Joel Villanueva: recording. Could you explain the capabilities nitong OBS as well as any considerations that investigators take into account pag ginagamit po itong recordings generated through this particular software as part of your investigation?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: Yung OBS po capable po siya i-screen record kung ano po'y nakikita sa screen. After po nun, makakapag-generate po siya ng output. Yung output po na yun, yung minamanually compared ko with the livestream video, Your Honor. To authenticate? Yes po.
Sen. Joel Villanueva: Thank you. Thank you, Sir Presiding Officer. Thank you. Thank you, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Noted and entered into the records. What is the pleasure of Senator Judge Rafi Tulfo?
Sen. Raffy T. Tulfo: Thank you.
Sen. Raffy T. Tulfo: Mr. Presiding Judge. Just a statement. The
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: gentleman may proceed.
Sen. Raffy T. Tulfo: In Rule 132, Section 17, it is not mandated that the whole record be shown to the court. The video being shown in open court and it being in evidence is completely different. That's all, Mr. Presiding Officer.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Noted and entered into the records. What is the pleasure of Senator Judge Pangalinan?
Sen. Francis “Kiko” Pangilinan: Yes, Mr. President. Just a one or two quick questions to the… The
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: gentleman may proceed. Witnesses will please answer the questions of Senator Judge Paulinan. He has two minutes.
Sen. Francis “Kiko” Pangilinan: Yes, Mr. Calilung. Ikaw eh nabangit mo kanina na nag-training ka. Yes, Your Honor. Hindi lang dalawang linggong training lamang ang nakuha mo. Tama ba yun?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: Dalawang linggo on the start. Pero during the ano po, during the nag-ano na ako, tinatrain po ako ng chief ko. During the process… So, continuing
Sen. Francis “Kiko” Pangilinan: training?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: Yes po, kasi nagpe-present po ako sa… At
Sen. Francis “Kiko” Pangilinan: saan yung training? Sinabi mong dalawang linggo, nabanggit mo ba?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: Sa office namin siya ginawa, pero ang nag-handled is MaxCore po.
Sen. Francis “Kiko” Pangilinan: Ano yung MaxCore?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: MaxCore Interventures.
Sen. Francis “Kiko” Pangilinan: Sa ano nga yun?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: Provider po namin ng forensic softwares. At
Sen. Francis “Kiko” Pangilinan: kumpanya siya? Yes
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: po.
Sen. Francis “Kiko” Pangilinan: Ng computer… Ng mga pang-forensic po. Pang-forensic. Okay. Thank you.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: May I be allowed to speak in Cebuano a bit? Mahimu ba kita magpadayon? In Tagalog it means, in English, can we proceed?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Counsel may proceed.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Thank you so much. Now,
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: in
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: what particular portion of the subject video did
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: the respondent utter that
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: she already
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: A
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: person to
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: kill the
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: President, the First Lady, and the former Speaker of the House of Representatives.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Are
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: you done?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Objection?
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Objection, Your Honor.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Your Honor, the question is misleading. There was no mention anywhere before that that the video Mentioned the killing of the president.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Yeah,
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: there's no mention in any testimony earlier. There's no mention that that video.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Your Honor, again, with all respect, the records will bear me out. Bases have been more than complied with. This witness mentioned many times over that the subject of investigation is the statement of the vice president that she already contracted a person to kill. The President, the First Lady, and the former Speaker, there's no basis for the objection, Your Honor, please.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Your Honor, may I ask for a readback? He was the only party who said that, Your Honor. Kindly use
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: the third party in referring to opposing counsel.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Yes, Your Honor. If I may,
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Your Honor. May I ask, Your Honor, for a—
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Let the counsel for
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: defense finish his statement.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: May I ask, Your Honor, for a reading of the transcript as the witness, to my recollection, never mentioned that the Vice President did those things.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Alright. If I may, Your Honor, please— Counsel, kindly— Lay the basis. Yes, Your Honor, please. Now, Mr. Witness, you said that your office, the NBI, conducted an investigation for a statement made by the Vice President noong Nobyembre 23 taong 2024. Naalala mo yun? Objection, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: What is the basis of the objection?
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Your Honor, it's leading.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Your Honor, please, if I may, Your Honor, please. Do you remember?
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Leading, Your Honor.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: If I may, Your Honor, please, I'm just giving in to what the defense wants. The record will bear me out. This witness mentioned so many times over that he investigated the statement of the Vice President uttering that she already contracted a person. The whole nation is listening. The Chair will
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: make a ruling. So
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: many words
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: leading. The
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Chair will make a ruling. The objection is overruled. Earlier, Chair noted. I have it in my notes. That the question was propounded by counsel with respect to the 11-23-24 incident that was the subject matter of a digital forensic examination by the witness pertaining to the former vice president. That was the instance, if the counsel will recall. That counsel for the prosecutors asked the witness if he knew who the vice president was. So the objection is overruled. Witness may answer.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Mr. Witness, naalala mo ba yung tanong?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Kindly repeat the question, Council.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: In what particular portion of
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: the subject video in that online media conference of the Vice President did she utter that she already contracted a person to kill the President, the First Lady, the former Speaker?
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: In
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: what portion? Objection,
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Your Honor. Sir, Your Honor, this honorable court already ruled on this question. The discussion later on was on the leading question made by the prosecutor. If you recall, Your Honor, this honorable court said, Prosecutor, please lay the foundation, the basis for your question. Your Honor, please, if I
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: make a response. The
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Presiding Officer will ask the witness. Mr.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Witness.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Out of the two or more so hours of video that you downloaded, do you know if at all the timestamp that pertains to any statements made by the Vice President pertaining to any of the allegations in the articles of impeachment, particularly Article 4, the subject matter of this case, in relation to alleged threats made by her in that video?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: Yes, Your Honor, but may I refer to my investigator's note, Your Honor?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: You may do so. Atty.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Alan Cayetano
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: May I
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: know from the records, is this the first time that the witness mentioned that the Vice President uttered threats against the President, the former Speaker, and the First Lady?
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Your Honor, if I may,
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: there
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: was no
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: mention at all. Because if it's the first time, precisely the rule says that you cannot allow leading questions. Whether it's from the judges, whether it's from the presiding officer or from the defense or the... So meaning, you lay the basis. Simply, you ask him, ano yung laman ng video? Pag binanggit na niya na may ganito sa laman ng video, then you can ask him na directly what parts. So all of us want to expedite it, but let's follow the rules. So that's why I'm asking, has this witnessed this afternoon? I missed a portion because I have a headache and I had to eat before I drink medicine but I was watching sa TV. Ba't hindi ko pa narinig na sinabi niya to? Kasi kung hindi pa niya sinabi, Mr. Presiding Officer, can we just follow the rules and just lay the basis? Ask him kung ano lamang ng video. Let him testify tapos pag binanggit niya yan, then you can ask him. Hindi na siya leading. But we shouldn't really ask leading questions because we'll violate the rules. So excuse me but I'll just be very particular when it comes to the rules. And it's not against any group. Senator
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Judge Cayetano, it will take some time before we can quote-unquote appeal to the records. I'm trying to have them get it. But in lieu of that, that's why the chair tried to intervene. Can counsel kindly lay the basis?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: For the witness to be able to identify the timestamp portions of the two-hour video. Counsel for the prosecutors may proceed.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: This will be quick. Mr. Witness, you said that your office conducted an investigation on the statement made by the Vice President dated November 23, 2024, correct?
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Objection, Your Honor.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Leading.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Overruled.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Witness may answer.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Yes, sir. Now, tanong ano ba, ano ba exactly yung sinabi ng Vice President nung araw na yan, November 23, 2024?
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Objection, Your Honor. I'm not yet done. Well, Your Honor, the pauses of the prosecution are very confusing. Kindly
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: let the counsel for the prosecutors finish his question
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: before you object. May I ask also the… May I ask… Instead of this, Your Honor, may I ask that the honorable court direct the witness to allow me to object before answering. Because precisely the questioning of the prosecutor
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: is
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: there are many pauses. It's confusing if he's done or not.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Witness even on occasion forgot what the question was because he did not respond to the question of the prosecutor.
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: Yes, Your Honor.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: So, I just...
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: just...
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Court will make sure of that.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Thank you, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: So, kindly finish your question if you want to state it again. Counsel for the prosecutors.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Maybe it's the tone.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: I'll be quick. What particular statements of the Vice President on that day did you investigate? Objection, Your Honor.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Vig.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Counsel for respondent. A bit of patience. Let the council finish. I don't think it's finished.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: The question is done. What particular statement on that day did you investigate? How is that leading?
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Objection, Your Honor. Vague.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Not leading.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: I didn't
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: say leading.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Council,
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: what's the basis of the objection?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Vague. Alright. I will indulge, Your Honor. I will indulge, Your Honor. I will indulge. I will add these two phrases. It will never be that. Now, Mr. Witness, what statements did the Vice President add on that day, if any? Your Honor, same objection.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: There's a 2 hour 26 minutes. Let the witness answer.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Counsel, this 2 hour and so minute video was done on the same day.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Correct, Your Honor. The question must be given with particularity. If
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: the witness knows, witness may answer. Answer. Answer. Witness will please answer.
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: Can I refer for my notes to identify the exact statement because I might said a statement that's not part of the actual statement.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Signing officer will allow the witness to refer to his notes to refresh his memory. Go ahead, Mr. Witness.
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: The specific statement, quote-unquote, Yes, huwag kang mag-alala ma'am sa security ko kasi may kinausap na ako na tao. Sinabi ko sa kanya kapag pinatay ako, patayin mo si BBM, si Lisa Araneta at si Martin Romualdez. No joke, no joke. Nag-bill-in na ako ma'am. Pag namatay ako sabi ko huwag kang tumigil hanggat di mo sila mapatay. Hanggat di mo sila mapatay sila. And then he said yes.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Please proceed counsel.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Thank you. Now. In what particular portion of that video recording that you authenticated of that online media briefing on November 23, 2024, did the Vice President utter
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: those words?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: If I may, Sir, I think we should include the question first. It starts at 1 hour and 15 minutes. To 1 hour 17 minutes and 18 seconds, sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Your Honor, so the witness manifested as an answer to the question in what portion he said, timestamps 1 hour 15 minutes 0 seconds to 1 hour 17 minutes 18 seconds and we computed, Your Honor please, it's a 2 minute 18 second portion of that video. At this juncture, Your Honor please, bases have been laid. The nation can finally see it. The court will do. We move that that two-minute and eighteen-second portion of that video be presented at this juncture. Your Honor, please.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: The secretariat is instructed to play the USB given to the tech behind that was observed and witnessed by both councils for the parties. Sorted. Kindly play the video.
Princess Maui: Vice President, thank you so much nga po para sa dala niyo Hopia nung hearing na pumunta kayo for PRRD. Kami yung nasa likod niyo po, yung pinawag nilang bastos kasi pumalakad
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: ni Congresswoman. Kindly pause it. Kindly pause it. Ganyan ba talaga?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Your Honor, please. Can I? Your Honor, please. The witness said that he would like to include the question propounded to the Vice President.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: So ganyan nga. Hindi na lalakihan yan. Ganyan na
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: talaga? Or it will get bigger?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: It will get bigger, Your Honor, please.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Okay. Please proceed.
Princess Maui: Thank you, ma'am. Nakakain kami. Apo ko'y natatakot kumain ng pagkain doon pa mamaya. Ma'am, mag-iingat po kayo. Nasa teritoryo pa yun ang kalaban. Okay lang po
Princess Maui: kayo, ma'am. Kasi sila naman top na eh. Sila talaga yung bastos eh. You reap
Princess Maui: what you sow.
Princess Maui: Mag-iingat po kayo kasi sa dinami-rami po ng inyong mga pasabog ngayong gabi, it seems like marami po talaga kayong alam about them, no? Dahil sa pagkakasama niyo sa kanila during the campaign and during the 2022 elections. Baka po mamaya kasi totoo yung mga naririnig namin or yung, I don't know if it's true, na meron daw silang Operation Romanovs and baka bala kayong ubusin ang inyong pamilya dahil hadlang kayo sa kanilang mga bala. In the future, so mag-iingat po kayo. Kami po kasi na kami ng EDSA Friday group, kami yung bumababa every Friday dyan sa EDSA because we believe yan yung tamang venue sa dinami-narami na ng problema natin. Ang kaya lang naman po namin gawin ay manawagan na bumaba na yan. Eh ano po kaya ang remedy naman yun yung mga nasa posisyon or yung mga kayang labanan itong napakarami na pong ginagawang? Corruption at crimen laban sa taong bayan. Ano po ang pwede niyong maging remedy para matapos na ito lalo't nagsisigaw na po ang taong bayan na mag-people power na?
Vice President Sara Zimmerman Duterte: Yes. Huwag ka mag-alala ma'am sa security ko kasi may kinuusap na ako na tao. Sinabi ko sa kanya kapag pinatay ako, patayin mo si BBM, si Lisa Araneta at si Martin Romales. No joke.
Vice President Sara Zimmerman Duterte: No joke. Magdilin na ako ma'am. Pag namatay ako sabi ko huwag ka tumigila hanggang hindi mo magpatay sila.
Vice President Sara Zimmerman Duterte: And then he said yes.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: That's the end of that 2 minute and 18 second portion of the video, Yon, please. Pwede ba kita magpadayon? Can we continue?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Council may continue, may proceed.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Now, Mr. Witness, what relation, if any, does that video
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: What happened next, Mr. Witness, kung meron man, after mong ma-authenticate yung subject video na yan?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: Previous statement of the Vice President that had similarities to the November 23, 2024 videos. Okay.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Now, sinabi mo that your team conducted yung tinatawag mong open source investigation for any prior statements made by the Vice President against President Marcos Jr. and his family members. Yung tanong nga, ba't kailangan pa mag-conduct?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: As part of our standard procedure, sir, kailangan namin makita yung full context kung bakit ito nagsimula. Kaya nagtingin kami ng mga prior statement, meet the vice president against the president and the family.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Alright. Now, ano ba yung naging resulta kung meron man sa naging open source investigation niyo, Mr. Witness?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: We identified a video October 18, 2024, an online press conference held by the Office of the Vice President, Sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Now, ano ba yung nakita niyo kung meron man sa naging press conference ng Vice President on October 18, 2024?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: There were similar statements uttered by the vice president against the president, sir. So
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: sinasabi mo na on that October 18, 2024 press conference may mga nasabi din ng mga statements. Yung vice presidente laban sa president. Yun ba sinasabi mo, diba? Yes, sir. Now yung tanong is ano ba yung naging mga... Parehong statements ng Vice President sa araw na yan, October 18, 2024.
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: To set the exact statement, may I refer to my investigator's notes, sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Move, Your Honor, that this witness be allowed to peruse his notes to answer the question as to ano ba yung naging exact statement ng Vice President on October 18, 2024, Your Honor, please. Witness may confer with his notes.
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: Quote and quote.
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: Gusto ko tanggalin yung ulo niya ba? I just imagine myself cutting his head.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Wait, wait. So sinabi ng vice president, gusto kong tanggalin yung ulo niya. I imagine myself cutting his head. Now, ano pa yung naging statement kung meron pa?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: So doon, na-realize ko, toxic na, di ba? Ganyan na yung imagination mo. Sinasakal mo na yung tao. And then, I said, this is over.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Alright. Kung meron pa, ano pa yung naging statement ng vice president sa araw na iyan?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: Hindi marunong maging presidente ang nakaupo. Kasalanan ko ba yun?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Kung meron pa, ano pa yung naging statement ng vice president sa araw na iyan?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: Hindi ko alam, pero isang beses sinabihan ko talaga si Sen. Aimee. Sabi ko sa kanya, kung hindi kayo tumigil, Hukukayin ko yung tatay niyo. Itatapon ko siya sa West Philippine Sea.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Your Honor, please.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: There is a manifestation of the good Senator Tito Soto. He did not hear the last statement.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: No. No such manifestation was heard by the Presiding Officer. Counsel may continue. Please proceed. Thank you so much.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Kindly stated for the record, Senator Judge Soto, apologies from the Presiding Officer.
Sen. Vicente C. Sotto III: Thank you. I did not get the exact words that were uttered during the last statement.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Will the witness kindly repeat his answer to the last question propounded by counsel for the prosecutors?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: Yes, Your Honor.
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: Hindi ko alam, pero isang beses sinabihan ko talaga si Senator Aimee. Sabi ko sa kanya, kung hindi kayo tumigil, Huwuhukayin ko yung tatay niyo. Itatapon ko siya sa West Philippine Sea.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Huwuhukayin. Huwuhukayin. May proceed, Your Honor, please. Counsel may proceed. Ano pa yung naging mga statements kung meron pa ng vice-presidente sa araw na iyan? Last
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: statement. Kung presidente niyo siya, okay lang. Ako hanggang vice-president lang ako. Anggang number two lang itong bansa na ito. Wala itong number one para sa akin.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Are these all the statements, Mr. Witness? Yes, sir. Now, proceed. Now, ano ba yung nangyari kung meron man pagkatapos madiskubre ng NBI yung mga naging statements ng Vice President nung araw na iyan, October 18, 2024?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: Like the, what we did to the Main video the November 23, I proceed to preserve and authenticate the October 18, 2024 video, sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Again, for ano ba yung ibig sabihin? When you preserve the video?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: It means that I make the necessary action to ensure that the evidence will be accessible at any time, sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Alright, now. Ano ba yung ibig sabihin? After mo ma-authenticate yung video, ano bang ginawa mo kung meron pa?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: I saved the video on my... Laptop and on a flash
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: drive, sir. Now, sinabi mo yung flash drive kung saan sinave mo yung mga video recording mo sa mga naging statements ng vice-presidente sa araw na iyan. Now, kung yung flash drive na iyan ipapakita sa iyo, maa-identify mo ba iyan? Yes, sir. Your Honor, please. We are now in the process of confronting this witness with a flash drive that is previously marked as Exhibit P. 14-11 small letter A for the prosecution containing the recording of the October 18, 2024 press conference of the vice president identified by the witness that is previously marked as exhibit P-4-11 for the prosecution.
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: Permission to unseal the flash drive.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: You may do so.
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: Thank
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: you, Your Honor.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Manifestation, honor, that the witness is in the process of checking the flash drive.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Question, Mr. Witness, what relation, if any, does that flash drive have with the flash drive you mentioned? This is the flash drive where I saved the recording, sir. Alright. Now, Mr.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Witness, you mentioned earlier That you authenticated the subject video by recording the same through open broadcaster software and then you compared the contents of the recording of the subject video and you also said that you found out that the respondent said, itong sinabi niya, gusto ko tanggalin yung ulo niya at saka I imagine myself cutting his head. Do you follow? Now, Mr. Witness. In what particular portion of that subject video did the vice president utter, Gusto kong tanggalin yung ulo niya? I imagine myself cutting his head. Permission to refer back to my
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: investigator's notes, sir. Witness may do so. Your Honor, may I approach the witness?
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Your Honor, may I approach the witness?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Counsel may do so. Thank you, Your Honor.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: For the
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: first statement, time stamp 1 hour 35 minutes 57 seconds to 1 hour 36 minutes and 10 seconds. And on the part na I just imagined myself, 1 hour 36 minutes and 52 seconds to 1 hour 36 minutes. What about
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: the statement that sinabi niya, so noon na-realize ko toxic na, diba? Ganyan na yung imagination mo. Sinasakal mo na yung tao. And then I said, this is over. In what particular portion of the video did the Vice President utter that statements?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: From the authenticated video, timestamp 1R. 38 minutes and 32 seconds to 1 hour 38 minutes and 48 seconds, sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Okay. Now, what about the statement, Hindi marunong maging presidente ang nakaupo? Kasalanan ko ba yun? In what particular portion of the subject video did the vice president utter that?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: Time stopped 55 minutes 26 seconds to time stopped 55 minutes and 37 seconds, sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Okay. Now, what about the statement that I quote, Hindi ko alam. Isang beses sinabihan ko talaga si Senator Aimee. Pag di tumigil, huhukayin ko ang tatay niyo at itatapon ko siya sa West Philippine Sea. In what particular portion of the video did the Vice President utter those words?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: Timestamp 1 hour 11 minutes and 28 seconds. To what are 11 minutes and 42 seconds, sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: And finally, as to the statements, I quote, Kung presidente niyo siya, okay lang. Ako hanggang vice president lang. Hanggang vice president lang ako. Hanggang number two lang itong bansang ito. Wala itong number one para sa akin. In what particular portion of that video did the vice president utter those words?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: One time stamp, one hour, four minutes and two seconds. 4 minutes and 16 seconds
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: With the subject video of that October 18, 2024 video that you identified. If any, okay? Now, Your Honor, we move that... Atty. Stephen Magallon, Atty. Stephen Magallon, be allowed to proceed to the technical booth to bring the flash drive and for the secretariat to play specific portions of the video identified by the witness.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Conditioned upon counsel being accompanied by a representative of the counsel for the respondents so that the exact same USB flash drive will be the one that will be played.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: To guide the secretariat, Your Honor, please, these are the timestamps that the prosecution would like to present. First, from 1 hour 35 minutes to 57 seconds to 1 hour 36 minutes and 10 seconds is the first video and the second video is from 1 hour 36 minutes 52 seconds to 1 hour 36 minutes and 58 seconds. So move, Your Honor, please.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Secretary is instructed to kindly play the video in the presence of both Councils for the Parties
Vice President Sara Zimmerman Duterte: Ang
Vice President Sara Zimmerman Duterte: galing niyang ulo niya ba?
Vice President Sara Zimmerman Duterte: I realized
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Cutting
Vice President Sara Zimmerman Duterte: his head Gusto
Vice President Sara Zimmerman Duterte: ko, ganun din ang gusto ko
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: You heard the vice president mentioning cutting
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: somebody else's head. Based on your investigation, based on your investigation,
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: kaninong ulo ba yung nire-refer ng vice president na gusto niyang tanggalin?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: The president, sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Ulo ng presidente?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: Yes, sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Mr. President, you also mentioned time stamps, 50s... 1 hour 38 minutes to 32 seconds and 1 hour 38 minutes to 48 seconds. May we have that specific portion be played?
Vice President Sara Zimmerman Duterte: So nun, na-realize ko, toxic na diba? Ganyan na yung, ganyan na yung imagination mo. Ang imagination mo, sinasakal mo na yung tao. And then I said, this is over.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Okay. Then, what about from time stamps? 55 minutes, 26 seconds to 55 minutes, 37 seconds, please.
Vice President Sara Zimmerman Duterte: Hindi marunong maging presidente ang nakaupo. Kasalanan ko ba iyon?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Okay. Now, what about from timestamps 1 hour 11 minutes 28 seconds to 1 hour 11 minutes 42 seconds?
Vice President Sara Zimmerman Duterte: Hindi ko alam, pero isang beses sinabihan ko talaga si Senator Imee. Sabi ko sa kanya, kung hindi kayo tumigil, huhukayin ko yung tatay niyo. Itatapon ko siya sa West Philippine Sea.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Thank you. What about from time stops 1 hour 4 minutes to 02 seconds to 1 hour 04 minutes 16 seconds?
Vice President Sara Zimmerman Duterte: Ano? Ay hindi. Hindi ko na gusto. Kung presidente niyo siya, okay lang. Ako hanggang vice president lang ako. Hanggang number two lang itong bansa na ito. Wala itong number one. Para sa akin. Yup.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Okay. May proceed, Your Honor. Mr. Witness, what relation, if any, do these portions of that specific video have with the video you authenticated as to the press conference of the Vice President on October 18, 2023?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: Those video presented were portions of the video that I recorded and authenticated, Sir. Thank you so much. Mr. Witness,
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: ano ba yung nangyari kung meron pa? After you authenticated, identified and authenticated the video ng vice president on October 18, 2024?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: We performed open source investigation to identify naman po yung mga naging responses ng iba't ibang tao in response to the statement of the vice president po.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Ano ba yung naging resulta kung meron man sa naging open source investigation niyo?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: We found that the president himself The former Speaker of the House and different governmental agencies made their statement in response to the statement of the Vice President.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: So yung Presidente, yung Speaker, former Speaker of the House, saka yung mga sinasabing mga governmental agencies nagbigay ng kanilang mga tugon sa mga nasabi ng Vice President. Now ano ba yung mga governmental agencies na ito that you are referring to aside from the President and the former Speaker of the House of Representatives?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: The Armed Forces of the Philippines The Philippine National Police The National Security Council And the Presidential Communication Officer Okay
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: now, nasabi mo na yung Presidente ay nag-issue ng kanyang statement in relation sa naging mga pahayag ng Vice President Ano ba yung naging pruweba mo sa naging statement ng Vice Presidente?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: I have taken a screenshot of the statement of the President on the official webpage of the Presidential Communication Office. And I also have a video recording which I authenticated wherein the President made such a statement, Sir. Okay, so nasabi mo,
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: isang screenshot saka isang authenticated recording ng Presidente. Now, let's go to that screenshot. Sino yung kumuha ng screenshot kung alam mo? I did, sir, and I used my laptop. Ginamit mo yung laptop mo. Ano ba yung ginawa mo kung meron man sa naging screenshot mo sa laptop mo? I first
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: saved an electronic copy po nung screenshot sa
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: laptop. Now, saan na itong screenshot? Pinrint ko po. Ha?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: Pinrint
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: ko po. Print mo. Now, saan na yung printout ng screenshot na ito? Sinabit ko po sa Committee on Justice
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: of House of Representatives.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Now, kung yung printout ng naging statement ng Presidente, sinabi mo, titled, Message by President Ferdinand R. Marcos Jr. is shown to you, will you be able to identify the same?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: Yes po.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: I'm showing you now a printout of a screenshot of the statement from the President, titled, quotes, Message from President Ferdinand R. Marcos Jr., and quotes, Your Honor, that is previously marked as Exhibit P-Roman numeral 4-12 for the prosecution through the website of the Presidential Communications Office. Now, question. What relation, if any, does this document have with the printout that you mentioned?
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Your Honor, same objections to this printout.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Yes.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: May I know the specific objection?
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Your Honor, same objections. There is on the left... Right bottom portion of the Annex P-U-12, 12A and until 12B, there are marked certified true copies from the NBI-signed sephirity dated 4-10-26,
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Your Honor. Court made a previous ruling about this matter already but the objection is duly noted.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Submit, Your Honor. Thank you. Mr. Witness, how faithful, please? How faithful, if at all, is this printout from the actual screenshots?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: The printout accurately reflects the screenshot, sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: And how do you know that this printout accurately reflects the screenshot?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: I compared the printout with the screenshot and the webpage were in the message.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Now, you mentioned that you authenticated the recording of the President making a statement. You mentioned that. Now, the question is authentication.
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: I did, sir. It's part of the January 30 affidavit of authentication of digital evidence.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Pagkatapos mo, sinabi mong nirecord mo, tsaka inauthenticate mo yung video ng presidente na nagbibigay ng statement niya.
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: Sinave ko po yung video sa laptop ko and sa flash drive.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: O, na-mention mo yung flash drive. Now, kung yung flash drive ipapakita sa'yo, ma-identify mo ba yan?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: Yes, po.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Now, Your Honor, please, we are in the process of confronting this witness ng isang flash drive that is previously marked for the prosecution as Exhibit P-Roman numeral IV-13, small letter A.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Permission to unseal the flash drive, sir.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Witness may do so.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Thank you, Your Honor.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Continuing manifestation that the flash drive contains the recording of the president making the statement that is previously marked as Exhibit P-Roman numeral 4-13 for the prosecution.
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: This is the flash drive where I received the recording, sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Okay, now, move that we allow Atty. Stephen Magalyon to proceed to the technical booth to have the recording played on, please. To be accompanied by the defense if they want to. So ordered.
President Ferdinand R. Marcos Jr.: Ang ganyang kriminal na pagtatangka ay hindi dapat pinapalampas. Yan ay aking papalagan. As a democratic country, we need to uphold the rule of law. Ako, bilang pinuno ng Executive Department at lahat ng mga nanunungkulan sa pamahalaan ay may sinumpaang tungkulin na tutup din at pangangalagaan ang konstitusyon at ang ating mga batas. Kaya hindi tama. Ang pagpigil sa mga halal ng bayan sa paghahanap ng katotohanan. Hindi na sanang hahantong sa ganitong drama kung ito at sa House of Representatives. Ang katotohanan ay hindi dapat itokhang. Tapos na sana ang usapang ito kung tutokhan ay magsabi ng totoo at hindi hahadlangan. Imbis na derechahang sagot, nililihis pa sa kwentong chicheria. Hangad ko na matuldo ka na itong mga pangyayaring ito sa parang matiwasay at magdadala sa atin sa katotohanan. Labindalawang taong din ako nanungkulan sa magkaparehong Kamara ng Kongreso. Batid ko ang kapangyarihan iginawan sa kanila ng taong bayan at ng ating konstitusyon. Dahil dito, ikinagalang ko ang kanilang gawa at ang buong executive branch. Lahat ng mga ahensya ay hindi nakakaligtas at parating suma sa ilalim sa kanilang masusing pagsusuri. Bilang isang bansa, marami tayong mga paghamon na dapat harapin at mga suliraning dapat bigyan ng lunas. Sa kabila ng mga pambabatikos, natin natin ikukumpromiso ang rule of law. Kailangan manaig ang batas sa anumang sitwasyon, sino man ang tamaan. Kaya hindi ko hahayaan magtagumpay ang hangarin ng iba na hatakin ang buong bansa sa burak ng politika. Igalang natin ang proseso. Ito pa rin ang katiwala sa atin ng milyon-milyon na Pilipino. Magtrabaho po tayo sa ikauunlad ng Republika ng Pilipinas at para matamo ang bagong Pilipinas.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Your Honor, the defense puts on record that the video was skipping, and then portions where the President—or who seemed to be the President—was paused while audio was continuing playing.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: So, it's delayed.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Yes, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Noted.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Thank you. Mr. Witness, what relation, if any, does that video of the President taking the statement, if any, have to the video of the President making the statement?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: That is the video that I recorded and authenticated, sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: All right. Now, proceed. You mentioned that the Presidential Communications Office, or PCO, also issued a statement. Ano yung pruweba mo na yung PCO nag-issue ng statement na iyan?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: I have a screenshot of the webpage of the Presidential Communications Office wherein they considered the statement of the Vice President as an active threat. As an active threat. Okay now, sino yung kumuha
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: ng screenshot na iyan? I did, Sir, and I used my laptop. Now, saan yung printout ng screenshot na iyan?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: Sinubmit ko po sa Committee on Justice of House of Representatives.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Now, aming ipinapakita yung isang printout ng isang screenshot galing sa website ng PCO kung saan yung statement, makikita yung statements ng Vice President, sinasabi ng PCO, that's an active threat. Now, previously marked in Exhibit P-Roman numeral 414. May you peruse the same. And after producing the same, the question, Mr. Calilung is, what relation, if any, does this document have with the print that you mentioned? But you have to produce the document first.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: For the record again, Your Honor, the... Council may proceed. Exhibit P-4-14 is a photocopy and on the right bottom part, there is a stamp mark. Certified Crew Copy NBI Signed, Sapphira T. Dated 4-10-26. The
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: observations and comments of the Respondents Council are duly noted.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Witness may answer.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Please peruse the document and answer the question, please.
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: This is the copy of the printouts that were submitted to the Committee on Justice, sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Thank you so much. How faithful, if at all, is this printout from the actual screenshot you mentioned? The printout accurately reflects the screenshots, sir. And how do you know that the printout accurately reflects the screenshots?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: I have compared the screenshot with the printouts and the webpage and found that the contents are identical.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Now, let's proceed. Mr. Witness, sinabi mo rin na yung former Speaker ng House of Representatives nagbigay rin ng statement sa mga pagbabanta ni VP of Duterte sa isang sub-video. Ano ba yung maging pruweba mo sa naging pahayag ng former Speaker ng House of Representatives?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: I have a video of the statement of the former Speaker of the House of Representatives during the
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: It's
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: part of the Affidavit of Authentication of Digital Evidence dated January 30, 2025 which I identified earlier, Sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Now, ano ba yung ginawa mo kung meron man after you authenticated yung video ng former Speaker of the House of Representatives?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: I saved a copy of the video on my laptop and a copy of the video on a DVD and a flash drive. Now,
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: sinabi mo, sinave mo sa isang flash drive. Kung yung flash drive na iyan ipapakita sa'yo, ma-identify ba mo ba yung flash drive na iyan? Yes, sir. Your Honor, we're in the process of... Presenting to the witness, yung isang flash drive that has been previously marked as Exhibit P-RN 4-15, subparagraph A, which contains the recording of the former speaker's speech previously marked as Exhibit P-RN 4-15.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Permission to unseal the flash drive, sir.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Witness label seen.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Thank you, Your Honor.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Manifestation, the witness is in the process of checking that flash drive.
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: This is the flash drive where I saved the recording, sir. Mr. Witness, question.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: In what particular portion of that video did the former Speaker of the House give his response to the threats of the Vice President?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: May I refer back to my notes?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Your Honor, Your
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Honor please. There is a request by the Witness that he be allowed to refer to his notes.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Yes, the witness may refer to his notes to refresh his memory. What is the pleasure of Senator Judge Erwin Tulfo?
Sen. Erwin Tulfo: Mr. Presiding Officer, just a clarificatory question. The witness here, for the record, mentioned that he was referring to notes. Kanina pa po ito. Could he please clarify what specific notes he was referring to? Who prepared those notes? When were they prepared? And were they made before, during, or after the events he had testified about? And also, these notes, nabigyan po ba ang defense ng Kapinto? Was this submitted as part of the evidence also, Mr. Presiding Officer? Additionally, the question is, was he relying on these notes to refresh his recollection while giving his testimony today?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Witness, will please answer the question of Senator Judge Erwin Tulfo.
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: This is my investigator's notes which I made during the time of investigation, sir.
Sen. Erwin Tulfo: My next question would be, was this also presented? Since notes niyo po ito, pinagbabasihan niyo po yung mga testimonyo niyo rito, nag-submit, sinabit niyo rin po ba ito as an evidence so that may refer din po ang defense?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: Mr.
Sen. Erwin Tulfo: Witness?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: Yung content po ng notes ko is nandun na po sa affidavit of investigation, sir.
Sen. Erwin Tulfo: Yung copy exactly ng notes. Hindi nyo naibigay. That's all, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Thank you, Senator Judge Erwin Tulfo. Counsel for the Prosecution.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Can
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: I make a manifestation, Your Honor, please, that the witness referred to his notes when answering specific questions as to... Actual statements made by the Vice President and the others, number 1 and number 2, in referring to the actual Atty.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: R.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Ligutan
Sen. Risa Hontiveros: Salamat po, Mr. Presiding Officer. Tig-isang tanong lamang po para sa witness at para sa prosecution.
Sen. Risa Hontiveros: Salamat, Mr. Presiding Officer. Mr. Calilung. Nung sinabi niyo na nag-conduct kayo ng open source intelligence, pagkatapos niyo ma-authenticate yung November 23, 2024 video, at nahanap niyo yung video naman ng press conference dated October 18, 2024, anong basis niyo para sabihin na yung mga statements sa October 18 press conference ay halintulad? Sa November 23 video na may assassination threat. In other words po, ano pong napansin yung magkakapareho dun sa statements nung October 18 at nung November 23? Or what do they have in common?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: Both were ang tinutukoy po, ang pinupunto po is yung president. And makikita po dun na hindi na sila in good terms nung October 18 pa lang po.
Sen. Risa Hontiveros: Okay, so sa parehong video ng press conference at saka yung November video naman, yung dalawang elementong yun, hindi na sila magkakasundo at
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: hindi na sila magkasundo at ang ina-address po ng, ang pinapatukuyang po ng vice president doon sa press conference is yung president po.
Sen. Risa Hontiveros: And then, Mr. Presiding Officer, salamat kay Mr. Calilung. Sa prosecution naman po yung isang tanong ko at this point in time, Mr. Presiding Officer. Well, Counsel, none of these statements are proof that the Vice President actually contracted an assassin or hired one. Why are these acts impeachable?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: There is an answer to the question, Your Honor, please. The prosecution is in the process of establishing that the Vice President should be impeached and be removed from office for contracting an assassin to kill the President, Your Honor, please. Inasmuch as we understand that these statements may not actually 100% prove that she in fact contracted an assassin. We are invoking a rule in the rules and evidence that there could be statements of a person that may not be directly similar to what he or she did, but it could establish what we call a specific intent, knowledge. Identity, Plan, System, and the like. Ibig sabihin po, pinapakita ng prosecution na yung mga nasabi ng Vice President sa gabing iyon, November 23, 2024, hindi po yan nag-iisang statement ng Vice President. Kung hindi, yun po yung culmination sa mga series of statements ng Vice President kung saan sinasabi niya talagang gusto niyang Patayin yung Presidente, yung First Lady, tsaka yung former Speaker of the House. Your Honor, please. We invoke Rule 130, Your Honor, please, Section 35 of the Rules of Court. Etong mga statements na to, they prove one thing. Talagang may plano na, talagang may system na, talagang may knowledge na yung Vice President sa anong gusto niyang gawin sa Pangulo. Gusto niyang pugutan ng ulo. Gusto niyang patayin. No less than the President of the Republic of the Philippines. At
Sen. Risa Hontiveros: ang tanong po ba dito ay kung may krimen o kung ang asal ay karapat dapat sa Vice Presidente?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: We are able to answer two questions, Your Honor, please. The charges against the Vice President ay yung pagbe-betray ng public trust, Your Honor, please. That is also, Your Honor, please, a culpable violation of the Constitution. Now, yung usaping, was that a criminal act? Yes, Your Honor, please. Kaya nga, yung NBI, through this witness, will prove na nag-file na. Nag-file na ng kaso yung NBI against the Vice President, exactly sa mga naging. Pagbabanta niya. But you know, Your Honor, I'm a lawyer, but I'm willing, willing to take off yung robe ko as a lawyer and answer the question directly. Mga kababayan,
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: kailan ba naging normal?
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Your Honor, this is no longer answering the question. We object, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Make an equitable ruling in a while. Kindly let the gentleman finish because it's a senator-judge asking a question of a party.
Sen. Risa Hontiveros: Thank you, Mr. Presiding Officer.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Kailan ba nangyari sa kasaysayan ng Republika ng Pilipinas na yung pangalawang Pangulo ng ating bansa nagbanta, sinabi sa publiko na nakipagkontrata na siya sa isang mamamatay tao Upang patayin ang pangulo, ang
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: first lady, yung asawa niya.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Now, Your Honor, please.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Yung pagpapanta ng Vice Presidente sa buhay ng Pangulo ng Republika ng Pilipinas, hindi po yan normal.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Iyan po ay unang pagkakataon na nangyari yan.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Nakipagkontrata sa isang mamamatay tao, Your Honor, please, to do that. Even without going into the question, is that a criminal act, Your Honor, please? That act, 110% sure, betrayed the public trust that the Vice President got in the previous elections. Thank
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: you.
Sen. Risa Hontiveros: Thank you,
Sen. Risa Hontiveros: Counsel. Salamat, Counsel. Salamat, Mr. Calilung. Salamat, Mr. Presiding Officer. Chair would
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: like to remind my colleagues.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: The question posed by Senator Judge Riza pertains to the final question of this entire impeachment proceedings already. If that is an impeachable act or not. And since we gave the counsel for the prosecutors I think about five minutes, Chair would now like to be fair and hear the counsel for the respondent to discuss why it is not.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: An impeachable offense.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Your honor, may I be allowed to do so after our cross? After your? I would like the, as I understand it, I would like the honorable court to play back what the prosecutor said. Because it's very interesting. So may I be indulged to allow to give my answer after my cross-examination? The chair will allow it. Thank you, your honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: But you would have the similar and same amount of time given to the counsel for the prosecutors, again, to answer the reverse of the question. Because statements were made by the counsel for the prosecutor, there are conclusions of fact and law already, which should be taken upon advisement by the impeachment court because these were not evidence, but rather conclusions in fact and law by the counsel for the prosecutor. Senator Judge Pia Cayetano is recognized. Ma'am, you may proceed. What's your pleasure?
Sen. Pia S. Cayetano: Thank
Sen. Pia S. Cayetano: you. Thank you, Mr. President. No, I would just like to manifest my support for the statement and observation of the presiding officer. That was like a closing statement, Mr. President. So, I don't think this is fair because, you know, some parts are exciting, some parts are dragging. We're trying our best to be paying attention and what evidence, you know, we have to fact the evidence before us, what is admissible, what is not. The official objections will come later. But when we allow this to happen, Nandashortcut na natin yung proses. So, if I may, with all due respect, Mr. President, admonish us. Call us out if yung question natin is also not proper at the proper time. We may all make those mistakes. Even I may make that mistake. And I'm telling you, please call me out if I make a mistake and ask the kind of question that should not properly be asked by a judge at that particular time.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Julie Noted and well taken. The chair, as I said, or as the presiding officer said earlier. I would like to make a ruling that the counsel for the respondent will be given, I think that was approximately 8 minutes or 10 minutes. We will get the exact time to answer after the cross-examination of this witness so that we would be fair. In listening and hearing the views of both parties in regard to the query raised earlier. Senator Judge Tia Cayetano?
Sen. Pia S. Cayetano: Sorry, Mr. President. I don't mean to interrupt. I want to give the defense a time. I respectfully move that the statements of the prosecution be stricken off the record. It is not proper for those statements to have been made. Thank you.
Sen. Pia S. Cayetano: Your
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Honor? If I may, Your Honor, please.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: With
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: the
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: permission of Senator
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Judge
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Mia Cayetano, may we
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: table her motion and act on it at a later time with respect to striking it so that we can discuss the matter.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Thank you for
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: your generosity, Senator Judge Pia Cayetano.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: For the record, we joined the motion of the Honorable Senator. No need,
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Counsel. That most of them will be taken up at the proper time by this Court.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: For the record though, to your honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Noted for the record, Senator Judge Erwin Tulfo first and then Senator Judge Rizal Deveras once again.
Sen. Erwin Tulfo: I think to resolve this issue, Mr. Presiding Officer, Mr. President, a quick manifestation. Can we request the Council that Atty.
Sen. Erwin Tulfo: G.
Sen. Erwin Tulfo: Ligutan, Atty.
Sen. Erwin Tulfo: Sa madaling sabi po, hinihiling lang po natin na kung mayroon nang nakahandang sinumpaang sa laisay ng susunod na testigo, Magbigay na sana ng mga kopya nito sa aming mga senator judges bago pa po ang pagdining upang magsilbing gabay sa pagtatanong at pagtatalakay. Maiwasan po natin ang mga sitwasyon na ito. Thank you, Mr. Presiding Officer.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: To reply, Senator Judge Erwin Tulfo, the court did not adopt the judicial affidavit rule for the simple reason that we wanted all of the testimonies to be made and given in open court, so that it will be heard not only by the senator judges but also by the public as a whole, given that this is an impeachment court and an impeachment trial that seeks to unseat a duly elected official. However, the court shall endeavor through the clerk of court to give the senator judges a copy of the annexes attached, if they have not yet done so, to the pre-trial order and the pre-trial briefs pre-marked by the parties, because it would encompass already approximately 80% of the documents that will be presented by both parties, save, of course, for documents that they have not yet been able to produce and are yet to produce. But the clerk of court is instructed to endeavor to do so with respect to the senator judges so that they can catch up with what is going on in the proceedings. Counsel for the prosecution, you may proceed.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Thank you so much.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Apologies. Senator Judge Risa Hontiveros is recognized. What is your pleasure, ma'am?
Sen. Risa Hontiveros: Salamat po Mr. Presiding Officer.
Sen. Risa Hontiveros: Statement of the Presiding Officer to this Senator-Judge. But for clarity, Mr. Presiding Officer, my question po had to do with how the evidence is material to the allegations in the articles of impeachment. Kasi nga po, hindi naman napapatunayan na the Vice President actually sought an assassin. I wanted to appreciate the evidence before me. In light of the articles of impeachment, if you wish to strike out the response of the prosecutor, then so be it, Mr. Presiding Officer. But for clarity again, my intention was not to provoke a closing statement. Thank you, Mr. Presiding Officer. We
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: will review the transcript again. Sorry, we have some... My apologies on the part of the Presiding Officer. We have a bit of a problem with respect to getting an updated copy of the TSN. But given the clarification of Senator Judge Riza on the matter, then for the consideration of the body, given that we tabled the motion of Senator Pia, that the response of counsel for the prosecution is not responsive to the question of Senator Judge Ontiveros. Because clearly the question he answered was whether or not it constituted an impeachable offense. But without further debate, we are tabling this. And we'll discuss and decide upon this at a later date. So, ordered. Thank you so much. May proceed, Your Honor, please. Counsel, may proceed. Mr.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Wittes? Okay. Now, sinabi mo na yung former Speaker of the House ay nagbigay ng kanyang tugon sa managing pagbabanta ng Vice President. Tsaka sinabi mo rin na may isang video recording na inauthenticate mo. Yung tanong is... I'm reminded he is supposed to answer the specific timestamp of that recording of the former Speaker of the House's speech. I move that the witness be allowed to answer the question as to ano yung naging specific timestamp ng recording na yan.
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: May I refer to my investigator's notes? Thank you, Your Honor.
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: Timestamp. 1 minute 2 seconds to 2 minutes and 20 seconds So
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: that would be timestamp 1 minute 2 seconds to 2 minutes 20 seconds sir 20 seconds Your Honor please I move that the portion identified by the witness from timestamps 1 minute 2 seconds to 2 minutes 20 seconds be played Your Honor please
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Clerk of Court is directed to coordinate with counsel for the prosecution accompanied by counsel for the respondent to make sure that the USB identified by the witness will be the same one that will be played. It's ordered.
Sen. Sherwin T. Gatchalian: The Senate President. Sir Presiding Officer, I just have a few questions while we're waiting for the video to play. This is in line with authentication. The
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: gentleman may proceed. Yes,
Sen. Sherwin T. Gatchalian: two minutes. At sa ating ginong testigo, narinig ko kanina
Sen. Sherwin T. Gatchalian: Anong ibig sabihin ng open source investigation?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: Ang ibig sabihin po nun is nag-gather po ko ng iba't ibang information na available sa internet wherein anyone can access po yung data na yun.
Sen. Sherwin T. Gatchalian: And yung iba't ibang information na yun, how do you prove whether those information are valid?
Sen. Sherwin T. Gatchalian: Are valid, authentic, in the age of fake news?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: Your Honor, information is from official websites and official web pages to ensure that the contents are accurate.
Sen. Sherwin T. Gatchalian: Okay. And then my next question: manual comparison of videos between, let's say, Facebook and, let's say, a video recording. Can you describe to us, anong ibig sabihin ng manual comparison?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: Ibig sabihin po nun, Your Honor, meron akong dalawang monitor during that time and both videos were being played to ensure that the contents are identical po.
Sen. Sherwin T. Gatchalian: Meron bang, ano yan, nakaupo ka doon, tinitignan mo yung dalawa? Yes po. Wala ka bang, let's say, software na will say, ito ay purely... Parehas itong dalawang video. Kasi ina-imagine ko lang upo ka doon, papanoodin mo yung dalawang video.
Sen. Sherwin T. Gatchalian: How do we know that one is to one yung video na kinocompare mo?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: Based on, nakikita naman po siya and based on the audio, sir, na sabay po sila.
Sen. Sherwin T. Gatchalian: Ikaw lang yun ang tumitingin?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: Yes po, and it was checked after po.
Sen. Sherwin T. Gatchalian: Sino nag-check?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: Meron po ako nagre-review na executive officer and the chief po.
Sen. Sherwin T. Gatchalian: So kayong dalawa ang nagsasabi na itong Facebook video and also itong video recording talagang parehas na parehas?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: The authentication itself na affidavit po, ako lang po.
Sen. Sherwin T. Gatchalian: Okay. Meron ba kayong ginagamit ng standards in terms of comparison? Like for example, Ito ay ginagamit ng International Investigative Body. Ito ay isang standard na acceptable by international judicial process. Meron ba kayong ginagamit na standard acceptable by the judiciary or any courts?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: Yung procedure ko po nagawa is based lang po sa digital forensic procedure po. Nino? Ayun po yung ginagamit sa digital forensic as a whole. Yung process po ng identification.
Sen. Sherwin T. Gatchalian: But yung Digital Forensic Procedure, ito ba internationally accepted procedure or locally lang?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: It's a procedure that is acceptable internationally in court po.
Sen. Sherwin T. Gatchalian: And then ano ang meron bang international accreditation stamp yan or organization that approves it?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: I have no personal knowledge, Your Honor, but I've been following that procedure.
Sen. Sherwin T. Gatchalian: And accepted by the courts? Yes po. Thank you, Mr. President.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Clerk of Court is directed through the technical staff to kindly play the video.
Ferdinand Martin G. Romualdez: The Vice President of the Republic of the Philippines, Sara Duterte, admitted to contacting an assassin to kill President Ferdinand R. Marcos Jr., First Lady Luis Araneta Marcos, and myself. Let me be clear. Hindi na ito biro. Hindi na ito normal na panalita. Isa itong direktang banta sa ating demokrasya, sa ating pamalaan, at sa siguridad ng bayan.
Ferdinand Martin G. Romualdez: Such statement is not just reckless, it is dangerous. It sends a chilling message to our people. A message that violence can be contemplated by those in positions of power.
Ferdinand Martin G. Romualdez: It is attack on the very foundation of our government. It is an insult to every Filipino who believes in the rule of law and the sanctity of life. Violence has no place in our society. It is irreconcilable with the values that have taught and guided us for years.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Thank you so much. Mr. Witness, nasabi mo rin na yung AFP, Armed Forces of the Philippines, nag-issue rin ng kanilang tugon sa mga naging pagbabanta ng Vice President. Ano ba yung pruweba mo sa naging tugon ng Armed Forces of the Philippines?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: I have a screenshot of the website of the Armed Forces of the Philippines. Title Statement on Military Professionalism and National Unity by Gen. Romeo Browner, Sir. Sinabi mo screenshot. Now, sino yung kumuha ng screenshot na iyan? I did,
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Sir,
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: and I used my laptop.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Anong ginawa mo sa screenshot na iyan kung meron
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: man? I first saved an electronic copy ng screenshot sa laptop and printed it. Saan na yung printout ng screenshot na iyan? Sinubmit ko po yung copy sa... Now,
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: kung yung printout ng screenshot ipapakita sa'yo, ma-identify mo ba yan? Yes, sir. Now, we are now in the process of presenting to you a printout of a screenshot from the AFP website with the title, Quotes, Statements on Military Professionalism and National Unity, and quotes that is previously marked as Exhibit P-Roman numeral 4-16. Okay? May you peruse the same?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: And the question is, what relation, if any, does that document have with the printouts of the screenshot you mentioned?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: This is a copy.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: How faithful, if at all, is this printout from the actual screenshots? The printout accurately reflects the screenshot, sir. How do you know that the printout
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: accurately reflects the screenshot? I compared the printouts with the screenshot and the webpage of the EFP and found that the contents are identical, sir.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Now, sinabi mo rin, Mr. Your Honor, for the record, we have the... Counsel, correspondent. We have the copy of the document. How can he be identifying the document when he does not have that copy? Are you following a script?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Oh, my goodness, Your Honor, please. I move that that statement by the defense that the witness is finally be stricken out of record. For the record, Your Honor, the witness was perusing the document before he handed that to the defense. I move that the statements of the defense be stricken out, Your Honor, please. But he was answering the
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: question. Comments of both counsels are simply noted. Kindly, if you're done with the document, counsel, kindly give it to the witness.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Your Honor, for the record, the right-hand portion of both documents contain certified true copies.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: It's a mere photocopy, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: The manifestation and objection is duly noted. Same ruling by this court. Witness may answer.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: You state
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: for the record your answer.
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: I have compared the screenshot with the printouts and the webpage and found that the contents are identical, sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Your Honor, may I continue? Mr. Witness, sinabi mo rin na yung PNP ay nag-issue rin ng kanilang statements sa mga naging pagbabanta ng Vice Presidente sa subject video. Ano buwang pruweba mo kung meron man of that PNP statements?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: I
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: have the screenshot of the statement of the PNP on their Facebook official page. Dated November 23, 2024, Sir. Sino bang kumuha
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: ng screenshot na
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: iyan? I did, Sir, and I used my laptop.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Anong ginawa mo sa screenshot na iyan, kung meron man?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: Sinip ko po yung screenshot doon sa laptop ko and print it.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: And then, print it mo. Saan na yung printout ng screenshot na iyan?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: Sinubmit ko po sa Committee on Justice on House of Representatives.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Now, saan na yung printout ng screenshot na iyan? Sinabit ko po sa Committee on Justice. Now, kung yung copy ng printout ng screenshot ipapakita sa'yo, will you be able to identify the same?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: Yes, sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Now, I'm
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: showing you a printout of a screenshot ng Facebook post ng PNP dated November 23, 2024. Title is PNP Statement that is previously marked as Exhibit P-14. Sorry, P-Roman numeral 417. What relation, if any? Your Honor,
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: may I ask that we be allowed to peruse before he asks his question to identify the document.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Counsel is directed to kindly give opposing counsel for the respondent a copy of the document being presented to the witness.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Your Honor, both documents appear to be photocopies, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Noted. And I presume the continuing objection and comment of the counsel-respondent will be placed on record as well.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Thank you, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Witness may answer.
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: It is a copy of the submitted document to the Committee on Justice, Sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: How faithful, if at all, is this printout sa naging actual screenshot?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: It accurately reflects the screenshot.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Tsaka paano po nasabi na that printout accurately reflects the screenshot? I
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: compared the screenshot with the printout and the web page where this was posted and found that the contents are identical.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Okay, so let's go to the last agency, Mr. Witness. Nasabi mo rin na yung National Security Council or NSC nag-issue ng statement sa naging mga pagbabanta ng Vice President. Ano mong prueba mo kung meron man sa naging tugod ng National Security Council or NSC?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: I have the screenshot of the Statement of National Security Council on the official webpage of the Presidential Communication Office, Sir. Sino yung kumuha ng screenshot? I did, Sir, and I
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: used
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: my laptop.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Okay, anong ginawa mo kung meron man? Saan naging screenshot
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: na iyan? Sinip ko muna electronic copy ng screenshot sa laptop ko. Saan
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: na yung screenshot na iyan kung alam mo?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: Pinurin ko, Sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Kung yung kopya ng screenshot na iyan ipapakita sa iyo, ma-identify mo ba? Yes, sir. Now, we are in the process of showing you a printout. The defense may produce a document. It's a screenshot ng National Security Council statement. Okay. Previously marked is Exhibit P-Roman numeral 4-18.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Your Honor, the Exhibit P-4-18 is a photocopy.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Noted.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Okay.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: May I ask the question?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Kindly return the document to the witness so that witness may answer.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Mr. Witness, what relation, if any, does that document have with the printout of the screenshot you mentioned? This is the copy that was submitted to the Committee on Justice, sir. How faithful, if at all, is that printout from the actual screenshot?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: It accurately reflects the screenshot, sir. And how do you know that that printout accurately reflects the screenshot?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: I conferred the screenshot with the printouts and the webpage and found that the contents are identical, sir. Done.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Now, Mr. Witness, let's proceed. Sinabi mo rin na in the course you conducted yung open source investigation now, what happened, if any, in the course of your investigation in relation to the statements of the Vice President after you collated the videos, the screenshots of the several governmental agencies?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: We then proceed to the issuance of subpoena, sir, to the following individuals who are present on November 23, 2024.
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: Bons Magsambol, Red Mendoza, Demce Reyes, Ana Malindog Uy, Mikael Flores, and Jason
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Rubrico, sir. Alright. Now, yung tanong, Mr. Witnesses, ba't kaya nag-issue kung alam mo, no? Ba't nag-issue yung NBI nang sabihin na sa mga tao nito?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: Ano ba yung
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: nangyari kung meron man after yung NBI nag-issue ng sa Pinas ba yan or sa PINAY sa mga taong ito?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: Dumating po sa office namin si Demsie Reyes and Bons Magsambol nung December 4, 2024. And Ina-sign po sa akin na i-interview at ako po yung nag-interview.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: So, Your Honor, please may Dempsey Reyes' soul rest in peace. Now, ano ba yung nangyari kung meron man during your interview with na mayapang si Dempsey Reyes?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: He confirmed po na he was present during the November 23, 2024 online press conference. And he also confirmed that He heard the vice president utter the statement, quote and quote. May I refer to the notes for the exact statement? The witness may do so.
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: He heard the statement of the vice president, quote and quote. Yes, huwag kang mag-alala, ma'am, sa security ko kasi may kinausap na ako na tao. Sinabi ko sa kanya.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: May I object? This is hearsay.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Objection is sustained. Counsel, clearly you're trying to use this witness to present an affidavit of another person who has already passed.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: If I may, Your Honor, please. Your Honor, please. That is not an affidavit of Dempsey Reyes, Your Honor, please. The question was what happened during his interview with that person. And he has just answered the question by saying that Dempsey Reyes confirmed that he was there and that he heard the Vice President uttering the statement, Your Honor, please. Does that hearsay, Your Honor, please? And be that as it may, Your Honor, please, we invoke. A doctrine that we call an independently relevant statement. The defense is reacting. I don't know why. Your Honor, please. IRS would allow this witness to testify as to what the other person told him as to that fact, the making of the statement. As to whether or not what the person said is true or not, that is not material at this point. Your Honor, please.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Let the court clarify then. As to tenor, the court will allow it. As to the fact, as to the supposed fact that the witness told this with, what's his name, Dempsey Reyes, made those utterances to the witness but not as to the truth of what Dempsey Kaiden Reyes said.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: As to subject to that clarification, court will allow it.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Counsel, proceed. Thank you so much, Your Honor, please. What about this Bons Magsambol? Ano ba yung nangyari sa interview with him kung meron man?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: Bons Magsambol also confirmed that he was present. Objection, Your Honor. Same objection.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: And same ruling,
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: I suppose.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Let the witness first answer and the court will make a ruling because you might have a different answer. Because, Counsel, note ha, the affidavit of the witness appended
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: The affidavit of this Bons guy but did not do so with the affidavit of Dempsey. So, court will listen, presiding officer will listen to the witness before ruling on the matter. We may have the same ruling unless he gives a different answer. Please witness, Mr. Answer. Please, Mr. Witness, kindly answer.
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: Thank you, Your Honor. Bons Magsambol also confirmed that he was present on the November 23, 2020 for online press conference held by the office of the Vice President. And he also confirmed that he heard the utterance of the Vice President making the statement.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Same ruling, only as to Tenor. The Court will admit it. Not as to the truth that indeed what Bon said is true. But only as to the fact that he told the witness those statements in the Q&A that they had. What is the pressure of Senator Judge Rafi Tulfo?
Sen. Raffy T. Tulfo: Mr. Presiding Officer, I just have some clarificatory questions for the-
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: The gentleman may proceed and he has two minutes.
Sen. Raffy T. Tulfo: Expert witness, sabi mo meron ka two weeks lecture experience as a digital evidence expert, is that right? Two weeks? Two weeks training. Wala ka ng iba pang training?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: I have been training on different digital forensic aspect. Dito sa
Sen. Raffy T. Tulfo: abroad meron?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: Meron po, pero yung specific sa photo and video authentication, yun po yung two weeks.
Sen. Raffy T. Tulfo: So, all in all, total, you have two years experience plus two weeks lecture lang pagdating sa authentication ng forensic evidence?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: For the photo and video, sir.
Sen. Raffy T. Tulfo: For the photo and video, which ito yung pinag-usapan
Sen. Raffy T. Tulfo: natin ngayon.
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: Yes, po.
Sen. Raffy T. Tulfo: Now, may question to you. In your testimony, Mr. Witness, you did mention that you personally investigated the alleged inciting to sedition by the VP Sara Duterte video,
Sen. Raffy T. Tulfo: correct?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: Yes, Your Honor.
Sen. Raffy T. Tulfo: Now, in doing so, in the course of your investigation, did you look at the comments section? If you did, ano yung mga reactions doon? Ano yung mga statements doon sa comment sections? Na mga nag-view ng videos?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: There are comments that they agreed to the statement of the Vice President, but it was not documented, sir. That's all. Mr. President and Officer, thank you.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Thank you, Senator Judge Tulfo. Council,
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: you may proceed. Thank you so much, Your Honor. Mr. Witness, let's proceed. What proof, if any, do you have that Dempsey Reyes confirmed that he heard the Vice President utter those words?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: I have the signed minutes of interview with Dempsey Reyes and an affidavit that I executed attesting to the interview, sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: All right. Now, what about this Bons Magsambol? What proof, if any, do you have that he confirmed that he heard the Vice President's uttered those words?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: I have the minutes of interview with Bons Magsambol, sir, that he was signed. And I also have the affidavit attesting that I interviewed Bons Magsambol, sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: So, so far, Mr. Witness, you mentioned one minutes and affidavits. Now, kung yung mga dokumentong ito ipapakita sa'yo, do you think you'll be able to identify the same? Yes, sir. Now, I'm now showing you a document entitled Side Minutes that is previously marked as Exhibit P-Roman numeral 4-20 and series.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Please peruse the documents.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: May the defense be allowed also to peruse, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: The defense may, the counsel for respondent may look at the document.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Your Honor, for the record, the documents marked as... Exhibit P-4-20 to P-4-20E are photocopies and Exhibit
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: P-4-20D is unreadable as well as P-4-20E,
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Your Honor. Which one is unreadable, Counsel? P-4-20D and P-4-20E.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: 20D?
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: D for
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Dog, Your Honor. D and E.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Delta
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Echo.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: What does P-4-20D seek to show, counsel for the prosecution? If I may produce the document, John, please.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Because indeed,
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: the presiding officer confirms that I cannot decipher what it seeks to show. Unless the photocopy of a photocopy is what I have.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: May we be given two minutes to secure the other copies of that document.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: P-IV-20E?
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Yes, Your Honor. This is
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: the one with the blurred face of the Vice President?
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Yes, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Supposedly on a computer?
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Your Honor, may we object on the two minutes? Because this is the document they are already having him identify.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Do they mean to correct that mistake?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Counsel, do not waste the court's time in regard to this.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Your Honor, if I may ask, we abide by the copies as they are. We abide by the copies as they are, Your Honor, please.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: So, let's see. Mr. Witness, what do you see in front of you? Insofar as P-4-20D and E is concerned?
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Sa parehong malabo yung kopya natin. Yan at yung kopya ko din.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Mr. Witness, if you don't see anything, it's okay.
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: I can only confirm the signed minutes, but the annexes, there are some unreadable, Your Honor.
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: But the signed minutes, I confirm, sir, that this is the... The what?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: The minutes, but not the attachments, because clearly the attachments P-IV-20D and P-IV-20E are both, um—
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: Yes, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: —unclear. Would that be correct?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: So only as to the supposed affidavit and not to the two attachments—you cannot identify them?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Noted. Thank you so much.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Now, on page four of the signed minutes, Mr. Witness,
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: there appears a signature above the name Dempsey Sidon Reyes. Whose signature is that, if you know?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: It is the signature of Dempsey Reyes, sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: How do you know that that is his signature?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: I saw him sign the document after our interview, sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Now, on page 4 of the sign minutes, may pirma din sa ibabaw ng pangalan ng isang. Atty. Jethro Lorenza A. Cuon. Kaninong signature ito kung alam mo?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: Signature of Atty. Cuon po who is the counsel of Dempsey Reyes and present during the interview, sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: And how do you know that that is signature?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: I saw him sign the document after the interview, sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Now, sa page 4 ng side minutes, let's go to page 4, Mr. Witness. Makikita mo dyan yung signatures sa ibabaw ng pangalang agent John Mark Calinong. Whose signature is that if you know? This is my signature,
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Okay now, you also mentioned ng affidavit. Kung yung affidavit na ito ay papakita sa'yo, will you be able to identify the same? Yes, sir. Now, pinapakita ko sa inyo now, yung affidavit dated February 10, 2025.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Your Honor, may we also be allowed to peruse? Yes. Thank you, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Kindly exhibit and show to counsel for the respondent the document you are showing to the witness.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: That is previously marked as Exhibit P-14-19 and series.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: And if the court may inquire as to the remainder of the testimony of this witness, we are about to wind up the testimony of this witness. Your
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Honor, for the record, this is a photocopy. This is Exhibit P-4-19.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Noted.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Okay.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Mr. Witness, have you perused the documents?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Have you perused the document? Nabasa mo na ba yung dokumentong iyan?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: Yes, sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Now, what relation, if any, does that document have with the affidavit you mentioned?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: This is the affidavit attesting may interview with them, sir. Yes, sir. Copy of the affidavit, sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Now, on page 2 of the affidavit, may makikita ang pirma sa ibabaw ng pangalang Agent John Mark Calilung. Kaninong pirma ba iyan? It is my signature, sir. Now, on page 2, may pirma din sa ibabaw ng pangalang Atty. Van Homer Angluben. Kaninong pirma ba iyan? Signature po ni Atty. Angluben, sir. Ba't mo nalaman na iyan ay isang pirma ni Atty. Angluben?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: I saw him sign the document and I have viewed and acted upon documents bearing his signature.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Thank you so much. Now, I'm now showing you the other affidavit of even date, February 10, 2025, that is previously marked as exhibit P-Roman numeral 4-21 and series. Can you peruse the same?
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Your Honor may be allowed. Thank you, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: So, counsel, for respondent, a copy of the document that the witness will testify to.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Thank you so much.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: For the record, Your Honor, the exhibit P-4-21 and exhibit P-4-21A are photocopies.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Julie noted. Kindly return the document to the witness for his perusal.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: We are returning the document to the witness here.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Council,
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: please proceed. Thank you so much, Your Honor, please. On what relation, if any, have you answered the question? Does this document have with the one you
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: mentioned? This is the copy of the affidavit of interview with Bons Magsambol, Your
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: Honor. Yes, please,
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: the copy, sir. Now, on page 2 of the affidavit, may perma sa ibabaw ng pangalang Agent John Mark Calilung. Kaninong perma ba yan? This is my signature, sir. Sa pahina page 2, may makikita din isang pirma sa ibabaw ng pangalang Atty. Van Homer Angluben. Kaninong pirma ba yan? This is the signature of Atty. Van Angluben, sir. Ba't mo nalaman na iyan ay isang pirma ni Atty. Angluben?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: Nakita ko po niya pinirmahan po document and may mga documents pa po ako nakita na pirmado niya.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Now, Mr. Witness, thank you so much. Now, we are showing you yung documento entitled Signed Minutes. That is previously marked Exhibit P-Roman numeral 4-22 and series. May you peruse the same. Defense may also peruse that document.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Thank you, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Kindly show a copy to the Council for Respondent.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Your Honor, Exhibits P-4-22 to Exhibits... P-4-22G are photocopies and exhibit P-4-22F Foxtrot and P-4-22G Golf are unreadable. For
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: the record, we are returning the document to the witness.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: For the record as well, chair confirms the observation of council correspondent in regard to P-4-22F and P-4-22G.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: And the presiding officer would like to once again ask the witness, can he decipher what is in the two exhibits mentioned by council correspondent? Again, P-4-22F, P-4-22G.
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: I can confirm the signed minutes but the attachments are unreadable, Your Honor.
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: Annex A and Annex B with Exhibit 4 -22F and P422G.
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: Thank you so much. May
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: procedure, please. On page 6 ng side minutes, may makikitang perma sa ibabaw ng pangalang Bones Magzambol. Magzambol, kaninong perma ba yan?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: This is the signature of Bones Magzambol, sir. Then, how do you know that perma yan? Sorry, ni Bones Magzambol.
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: Nakita ko po ito nung sinign po niya document after ng interview.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Now, you go to page 6 ng side minutes na yan. May makikita ang perma sa ibabaw ng pangalang Atty. Michael Christopher De Castro. Kaninong perma ba yan kung alam mo?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: Perma po ito ni Atty. De Castro. Counsel po ni Bons Magsambol during the time ng interview na present during that time.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Yung
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: tanong is paano mo nalaman na
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: yan ay perma ni Atty.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: De Castro?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: Nakita ko pong pinirma niya ito after yung interview, Sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Now, let's go to page 6 of that minutes. May makikitang pirma sa ibabaw ng pangalang Agent John Mark Calilung. Kaninong pirma ba yan? Pirma ko po, Sir. Okay. Now, Mr. Witness.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Mr. Witness, you mentioned that the NBI conducted an investigation on the threats uttered by the Vice President against the President. The First Lady, at saka former Speaker of the House of Representatives. Now, ano ba yung nangyari? Ano ba yung nangyari kung meron man pagkatapos ng naging investigasyon ng NBI?
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Objection, Your Honor. Misleading. He assumes as fact, not testified to by the witness.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Kindly rephrase, Counsel.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Okay, now. What happened next, if any? And if you know... And in relation to the investigation conducted by the NBI, after the NBI's investigation.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Objection, Your Honor. Same objection.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Your Honor, please, if I may.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Witness may answer.
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: After
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: the investigation, we executed an affidavit of investigation and recommended the filing of inciting to the decision and three counts of creep. Both in relation to Cybercrime Prevention Act of 2012, Sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Now, sinabi mo na yung NBI, you signed, executed yung affidavit of investigation, correct? Our team, Sir. Now, ano ba yung nangyari? Kung meron man, at saka kung alam mo, okay? Pagkatapos, ma-execute ang affidavit of investigation na yan in relation to the investigation you did on the vice president.
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: We filed it to the DOJ, the affidavit of investigation, together with its annexes, sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Okay. You said you filed the affidavit. Now, question. Ano yung mga nangyari kung meron man? Kung alam mo, after ma-file yung affidavit of investigation, What is the relationship with the DOJ in relation to the investigation you conducted in the Vice President?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: We further conduct an investigation wherein we identified different videos, at least three, that we find relevant to the November 23, sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Okay, so you are now mentioning videos. Sinabi mo relevant. Relevant again to what? To the November 23, 2024 video, sir. Alright. So, for the record, this is now the third set of videos you're referring to. Yes, sir. Now, ano yung mga videos na ito kung alam mo, Mr. Witness?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: The June 19 video wherein the Vice President resigned. As the Secretary of the Department of Education, the July 11 video wherein the Vice President state that she would not attend the SONA but instead declare herself as the designated survivor. And lastly, the November 26 video wherein the Vice President did not deny making statement but Instead, confirmed that she already talked to someone to kill the President, the First Lady, and the former Speaker of the House if she was killed.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: So for the record, you mentioned three videos. One is dated June 19, 2024, June 11, 2024, tsaka November 26 ba yun? Let's go to this video na sinabi mo ng vice president resigning as the secretary ng Department of Education on June 19. Ano yung pruweba mo? Sinabi mo rin na authenticate mo yung video, correct? Ano yung pruweba mo that you authenticated this video?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: I have executed an affidavit of authentication of digital evidence dated April 30, 2026, sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Kung yung kopya ng Affidavit of Authentication now dated, sinabi mo, April 30, 2026, maipapakita sa iyo. Okay? Ma-identify mo ba yan? Yes, sir. Now, we are in the process of showing you yung isang Affidavit of Authentication of Digital Evidence dated April 30, 2026 that is previously marked as Exhibit P-Roman Numeral 4-25 and Series. Defense is in the process of the manifestation of perusing that document. Your
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Honor, exhibit P - Council for the respondent. Thank you, Your Honor. Exhibit P-4-25 to exhibit P-4-25F Foxtrot are photocopies, Your Honor. And exhibit P-14-25B P-14-25F Fox Shot P-12-25B is unreadable and it merely shows a black screen. Meanwhile, P-4-25F seems to be a photocopy of a USB with no real USB attached. For the record, we are returning the document.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Mr.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Witness, the question is, what relation, if any, does that document have with the affidavit you mentioned?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: This is a copy of the Affidavit of Authentication of Digital Evidence dated April 30, 2026, which I executed. And on the annexes... On Annex B, there is a missing part.
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: It may be due to... I can't read some words on Annex B.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Mr. Witness, when you say Annex B, you're referring to Exhibit P-4-25C.
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: Yes, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: For the record, please proceed.
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: And also on Annex D, Exhibit P-4-25E, there is some missing, but...
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: The only missing is the hash file. Maybe due to printing.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: So it's not recognizable.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: For the record, Your Honor, the hash file is missing. The witness said dash file is missing.
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: The hash
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: file is missing as stated by the witness. Please proceed, Mr. Witness. How about P-425F?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: Yes, I confirm, Your Honor, that's a photograph of the flash drive.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: What do you confirm, the picture of the USB?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: Yes, Your Honor, a picture of the flash drive.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Your Honor?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Please proceed, Counsel, for the prosecution.
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: But this is the Affidavit of Authentication
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: of Digital Evidence. Okay, could you repeat your answer?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: This is the Affidavit of Authentication of Digital Evidence that I executed, but there are, on the annexes that I mentioned, there are some that
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: are unreadable. Thank you. May I make a manifestation, Your Honor, please? As to this affidavit, it pertains to a video. As to the video of the Vice President resigning, Your Honor, please. And we're supposed to present the flash drive that the defense pointed that they only have the photocopy. Be that as it may, Your Honor, please, we are waiving the presentation of the video of the Vice President resigning because, Your Honor, in the pre-trial order. Specifically on page 3 thereof, the defense already admitted that the vice president resigned on June 19, 2024. The
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: presiding officer was exactly about to state that. There is no need for the counsel, for the prosecution to present evidence on an admitted theft.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Thank you so much, Your Honor, please. May I proceed, Your Honor, please?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Counsel, may I proceed?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Now, Mr. Witness, you also mentioned that you authenticated a video Where the Vice President said that she would not attend the SONA and instead publicly declared herself as the, quote, designated survivor, end quote. What proof, if any, do you have that you authenticated the video?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: It's part of the affidavit of authentication of digital evidence dated April 30, 2026, which I previously identified, sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: What happened next, if any, after you authenticated the video of the vice president announcing that she is keeping the sauna and declaring herself as a designated survivor? I
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: saved the video on my laptop and saved a copy on a flash drive, sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: You saved a copy in a flash drive. Now, if this flash drive containing the video where the vice president said she declared herself as a designated survivor After skipping the Sona is shown to you, will you be able to identify the same?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: Yes, sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Now, we are now in the process of confronting you with a flash drive that is previously marked as Exhibit P-Roman numeral 4-24 small letter a for the prosecution containing the recording of the vice president where she said that she would not attend the Sona and instead declared herself as the quotes designated survivor and quote previously marked exhibit p dash roman numeral 4 that's 24 for the prosecution permission to unseal the flash drive
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: sir thank you your honor this
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: is the flash drive where i saved the recording sir
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: now
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: you also mentioned that you authenticated a video that on november 26 2024 the vice president did not deny
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: And instead confirmed her utterances of contracting an assassin to kill the president and the two others. What proof, if any, do you have that you authenticated the video?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: I have executed an affidavit of authentication of digital evidence dated April 27, 2026, sir. And
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: then aside from that, aside from that affidavit, do you have other proof, if any? For
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: objection, Your Honor, leading.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: If any, Your Honor, if any. It's still answerable by yes or
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: no. Yes, sir.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Ask and answer, Your Honor, please. Your
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: Honor, please,
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: can the witness be directed to wait until the court rules on an objection before answering? The witness is so
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: directed. Thank
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: you, Your Honor.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Ask and answer. So what is that, if any? Yes,
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: sir. I also executed an affidavit of authentication of digital evidence dated June 11. So
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: you mentioned two affidavits in result, correct, Mr. Wites? Yes,
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Mr. Wites, I'm showing you a document entitled Affidavit of Authentication of Digital Evidence dated April 27, 2026 that is previously marked as Exhibit P-Roman numeral 4-27 and series. May you peruse the same. Defense, your honor, manifestation is in the process of Perusing the same documents.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Your
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Honor, for the record, the exhibit P-4-27 to exhibit P-4-27D are photocopies and on exhibit
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: P-4
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: -27D it would seem to be a mere photocopy of a USB. An image of a USB and no actual USB appended.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Chair confirms the observation of the council for responding insofar as P-4-27D is concerned. May
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: I proceed, Your Honor, please?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: I will return the document to the witness so that he may answer.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: So what relation, if any, does that document have with the affidavit that you mentioned?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: This is a copy of the Affidavit of Authentication of Digital Evidence that I executed, sir, dated April 27, 2026, sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: And on page 2 of that affidavit, may makikitang perma sa ibabaw ng pangalang John Mark Calilung. Kaninong perma ba iyan? Signature ko, sir. Then, sa page 2 ng affidavit, may makikitang perma sa ibabaw ng pangalan ng isang Atty. Rhea Vanessa Asuncion. Kaninong perma ba iyan? Perma po ni Atty. Asuncion, sir. At paano mo nalaman na iyan ay isang perma ni Atty. Asuncion?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: I saw when she signed the document and I have acted upon documents bearing her signature, sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Okay. Mr. Witness, you also mentioned of the other affidavit on the collection preservation. You said it was dated June 11, 2026, right? Yes, sir. Now, if that affidavit will be shown to you, will you be able to identify that affidavit? Yes, sir. Now, I'm showing you, the prosecution is showing you a copy of that affidavit. That is previously marked in exhibit P-Roman numeral 4-28 and series for the prosecution. May you peruse the same.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: And for the record, Your Honor, I'm about to ask a few more questions and the prosecution is finally done with this first witness, Your Honor, please.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Noted.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Counsel, respondent.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Your Honor, for exhibits P-4-28 to exhibits To exhibit P-4-28H, these are photocopies. And Your Honor, we note the affidavit on the collection, preservation, and authentication of digital evidence in page 2, which is exhibit P-4-28A, mentions a copy of an affidavit of authentication of digital evidence dated January 30, 2025 is attached herewith as Annex A under Footnote 1 but upon perusal no Annex A is attached to the affidavit. On Exhibit P-4-28B under Footnote 2 it says a copy of the preservation request dated 24 November 2024 is attached as Annex B. But we note that there is no preservation request or annex be appended.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: As footnote number three of the same exhibit, a copy of the email dated November 28, 2024 from Meta is attached herewith as Annex C. However, no Annex C is appended upon the affidavit.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Footnote number four it says a copy of the authenticated recording of the video of the online live stream press conference of the vice president held on 23 November 2024 and it says it's attached here as Annex D however no Annex D is attached on this affidavit as a footnote number five a copy of the print out of the screenshot of hash file VP November 23 Press Con at the Batasan is attached here with this Annex E. However, no hash value or printout thereof is appended as any Annex E. For footnote 6 of the same exhibit, it says a copy of the VP November 23 Press Con at Batasan CCD transcript is attached as Annex F. and a copy of the Affidavit of Transcription dated December 2024 is attached as Annex G. However, no Batasan CCD transcript of the November 23 Prescon or Affidavit of Transcription are attached as Annexes F or G respectively. For Exhibit P-4-28C, the Footnote 7 says a copy of authenticated 18 October 2024 video is attached as Annex H. However, no Annex H or an authenticated video is attached hereon. As footnote number 8, a copy of the printout of screenshot of hash file is attached as Annex I. However, no printout of such hash file is found on this document.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: On exhibit P-4-28D, footnote 9 says a copy of the VPSD brief press briefing dated 18 October 2024 CCD transcript is attached as Annex J and a copy of the affidavit of transcription dated 3 February 2025 is attached As Annex K. However, no press briefing or affidavit of transcription dated February 3, 2025 are appended as Annex K. With the permission
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: of the Council for Responding to abbreviate the proceedings, Council for the Prosecution, will you stipulate that none of the attachments contained in the footnote until Annex K. K. If I may. Is attached to the affidavit that you are presenting the witness?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: If with a counter manifestation, Your Honor, please, that this latest affidavit of authentication tries to summarize each and every other affidavit authentication. So as to the concern of the defense, Your Honor, please, this is just a summary of all the other affidavits of authentication.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Subject to that qualification, but indeed it did not contain and does not contain or... The annexes purported to be part of this affidavit. Does councilor
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: respond and confirm that it is up to annex KK?
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Your Honor, we confirm. KK? Tama ba?
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: We confirm that is it until... KK, Your Honor. KK.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Noted subject to the brief manifestation of council, but indeed the chair, the preceding officer confirms that none of the annexes contained in all of the footnotes until annex KK. is attached to the affidavit being presented to the witness.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Your Honor, please. Thank
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: you so much.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: May I proceed? Mr. Witness. For the record, we're returning the document to the witness. Mr. Witness, have you perused the documents?
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: Yes, sir. This is a copy of the Affidavit of Authentication Collection Preservation Authentication of Digital Evidence, dated June 11, 2026. And it doesn't have annexes here.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: May
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: I proceed, Your Honor, please?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Mr. Vitez, what happened next, if any, after you authenticated the video of the vice president, the video of the vice president, that on November 26, 2024, you said, the vice president did not deny that she made the threats and, in fact, she confirmed her utterances? Should something happen to her? What happened next, if any, after that?
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Objection, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: What is the objection of counsel?
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Misleading,
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Your Honor. No mention. The witness did not mention this.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Witness may answer.
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: I saved the video of the November 26, 2024 online interview on my computer and on a flash drive.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Now, Your Honor, before counsel proceeds, may I request that counsel for the prosecution refrain from characterization—testifying on what the document or the video is. So, Your Honor, I request that.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Your Honor, I'm just merely describing an affidavit or a document or an object that this witness already testified to. I'm just repeating what the witness said. I'm not adding any value whatsoever to what the witness already testified to, Your Honor, please.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Precisely, Your Honor.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: And there's nothing wrong with that.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Nothing in the rules would disallow me to do that, Your Honor, please.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Will counsels kindly wait for the Presiding Officer to recognize them before they speak? The Chair will instead advise the senator judges to kindly listen, take note only of the pieces of evidence presented through a witness under oath and subject to cross-examination, and not statements made by either counsel that are conclusions of fact and/or law in arriving at their decision. The Chair will be more mindful of counsel for respondent insofar as that is concerned. Thank you. Counsel for the prosecution, you may proceed.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Thank you. Mr. Witness, you mentioned a flash drive, correct? Yes, sir. Now, kung yung flash drive na iyan ipapakita sa iyo, ma-identify mo ba yan? Yes, po. Now, ngayon ipinapakita ko yung flash drive na previously marked as Exhibit P1426 containing... The video recording of the Vice President on November 26, 2024 that is previously marked as Exhibit P-Roman numeral 426. May you peruse the same. Permission to unseal the
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: flash
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: drive, sir.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Witness may do so.
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: Thank you, Your Honor.
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: This is
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: the flash drive where I saved the recording, sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Thank you so much.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Now.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: You mentioned that you authenticated the recording of the video of the vice president on November 26, 2024. Okay, you said the vice president did not deny that she made the threats. In fact, she made the address. Not yet done, Mr. Witness. Now, the question now is, in what particular portion of that video did the vice president did not Did the vice president not deny that she made those threats? If you know.
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: Permission to refer to my investigator's notes, sir.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: You may do so.
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: Thank you, your honor.
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: Timestamp 10 minutes and 40 seconds to timestamp 11 minutes and 50 seconds. So
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: it's from timestamps 10 minutes to 40 seconds to 11 minutes 50 seconds. Quick calculation. That would be 1 minute and 19 seconds. Yes, sir.
John Mark Sta. Ana Calilung: 1
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: minute and 10 seconds. I'm about to show you now that 1 minute and 18 seconds portion, particularly from timestamps, 10 minutes, 40 seconds to 11 minutes, 50 seconds.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: May we allow Atty. Steven Magallon?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Will one of the counsel's correspondents accompany the counsel for the prosecution to make sure that it is the same USB identified by the witness that will be played by the tech
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: of
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: the clerk of court?
Vice President Sara Zimmerman Duterte: So I answered, I was asked Romanov and then I answered I was told by two people this is the first time I've heard of Romanov so that is the third already and and I said don't worry about my security if they kill me if I die kapag pinatay ako or kapag namatay ako in the context of don't worry about my security so this means pinatay ka
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Last
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: question for this prosecution witness. You can proceed. Mr. Witness, when confronted with the question whether she uttered those threats against the President, the First Lady, and the former Speaker of the House,
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: the Vice President did
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: not deny and she confirmed she made those threats. Objection, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: What is the objection?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Leading.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Witness.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: May not
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: answer. Counsel, kindly rephrase. It's your last question. That's a kindly rephrase.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Okay. Now, Mr. Witness, base sa video na iyan, makikita mo ba, base sa video na iyan, na yung Vice President, instead of denying, she confirmed that she made those threats.
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Objection. Leading.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: I will withdraw the question. That's all for this witness. Your Honor, please. Thank you very much.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Bugso ng kahilingan ng ilan sa aming mga miyembro dahil sa kapasyahan na rin ng presiding officer, ipagpapaliban natin ang cross-examination ng counsel for respondent para bukas. The witness is under the same obligation to appear tomorrow by virtue of the same subpoena issued to him. The same is true with respect to Atty. Jeremy Lontoc. Especially given that the subpoena gives two dates for the required appearance of the two NBI agents.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Any other points that any of the parties wish to make before we adjourn? Yes.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Counsel for the prosecution. For the record, the exhibits, in particular the flash drives, were unsealed. May I move that representatives from both sides be present to seal again those flash drives, and for countersignatures from both sides, please.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: We were worried about that, but I was waiting for counsel to actually ask for that. When can we do this? Would counsels for the parties wish to remain after, just so that we can sign and seal the USB?
Atty. Carlo Joaquin T. Narvasa: Of course, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Thank you. There being no other matters to be taken up by this court, the trial is hereby adjourned until 2 p.m. of Wednesday, July 8, 2026 for the continuation of the testimony of NBI agent John Mark Calilung, specifically the cross-examination by counsel for the respondent. Hearing is adjourned.